<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The custumers alphabet and primer Conteining, their creede or beliefe in the true doctrine of Christian religion. Their ten commandementes, or rules of ciuill life and conuersation, daily grace, generall confession, speciall supplication and forme of prayers. Togither with a pertinent answere to all such, as eyther in iest or in earnest, seeming doubtfull themselues, would faine perswade others, that, the bringing home of traffique must needes decay our shipping. All tending to the true and assured aduancement of his Maiesties customes, without possibility of fraude or couyn. Alwaies prouided, in reading read all, or nothing at al.</title>
            <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1608</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 23 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A07548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 17927</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114606</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849831</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15002</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A07548)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15002)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 722:2)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The custumers alphabet and primer Conteining, their creede or beliefe in the true doctrine of Christian religion. Their ten commandementes, or rules of ciuill life and conuersation, daily grace, generall confession, speciall supplication and forme of prayers. Togither with a pertinent answere to all such, as eyther in iest or in earnest, seeming doubtfull themselues, would faine perswade others, that, the bringing home of traffique must needes decay our shipping. All tending to the true and assured aduancement of his Maiesties customes, without possibility of fraude or couyn. Alwaies prouided, in reading read all, or nothing at al.</title>
                  <author>Milles, Tho. (Thomas), 1550?-1627?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[44] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by William Jaggard?],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1608.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Tho: Milles.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name conjectured by STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-L² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  Commerce --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CVSTVMERS ALPHABET and Primer.</p>
            <p>Conteining, Their CREEDE or Beliefe in the true Doctrine of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion.</p>
            <p>Their TEN COMMANDEMENTES, or Rules of Ciuill life and Conuerſation, dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Grace, generall Confeſſion, ſpeciall Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication and Forme of Prayers.</p>
            <p>Togither With a pertinent Anſwere to All ſuch, as ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in ieſt or in earneſt, ſeeming doubtfull themſelues, would faine perſwade others, that, the bringing home of Traffique muſt needes decay our Shipping.</p>
            <p>All tending to the true and aſſured aduancement of his Maieſties Cuſtomes, without poſsibility of fraude or Couyn.</p>
            <p>Alwaies prouided, In reading Read all, or nothing at al.</p>
            <p>ADSIT REGVLA. 1608.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="alphabet">
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>A A</hi> a. e. i. o. u. <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> b. c. d. f. g. h. k. l. m. n. p. q. r. ſ. t. w. x. z. <hi>&amp; perſe. Con, perſe. title, title,</hi> Eſt, Amen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORABLE MY SPECIAL GOOD LLL: <hi>THOMAS</hi> BARON OF <hi>BVCKHVRST,</hi> Earle of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> and <hi>Lord-Treaſurer</hi> of England. <hi>Henrie</hi> Lord <hi>Howard</hi> of <hi>Marnehill,</hi> Earle of <hi>Northampton,</hi> &amp; Lord-Warden of the <hi>Cinq-Ports.</hi> And <hi>Robert</hi> Baron of <hi>Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Vicount <hi>Cranbourne,</hi> Earle of <hi>Saliſbury,</hi> and Principall Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarie of State to the KINGS Maieſtie. All Knights of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER, and Lords of his Highneſſe moſt Honourable <hi>Preuy-Counſell.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y Dutie and Seruice to you honorable <hi>L.L.L.</hi> euery way humbly premiſed: I haue thought it good to preſent the ſame with the loyall Endeuours of a willing mind, though feeble wit, and weaker brayne; the Argument I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe being of a higher pitch and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter compaſſe, then I did imagine whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I tooke it in hand.</p>
            <p>Hazard at the firſt did much diſcourage me, &amp; in the mids, by Friendes I had been diſſwaded in regard of the paines, but for th' <hi>Enthouſiaſme</hi> ſtill ſounding in mine eares.</p>
            <q>Ton Ame ne doibt, ta flamme eſt ſi diuine, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Thy Soule is ſo beſet by vowes that are deuine,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt not tread amiſſe, why ſhould thy hart decline?</l>
            </q>
            <p>By whoſe perſwaſion whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had but begun, my Conſcience thruſt me forward, and thus preuailed at last.</p>
            <q>Ie veulx qu'un bel oſer, &amp;c.</q>
            <q>
               <l>Then dangers ſtand aſide, tis <hi>GOODNES</hi> calls me to it,</l>
               <l>If ought doe put me by, t'is <hi>WISDOMS</hi> hand ſhall do it.</l>
            </q>
            <p>My ſtayes beſides were theſe: That <hi>TRVTH</hi> was all my <hi>Ground,</hi> which as <hi>Time</hi> did ſuggest, <hi>Experience</hi> ſtill ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyd. My Pen <hi>OPORTET</hi> made, and was euer apt to mend: But <hi>ORDER</hi> gaue the <hi>Forme,</hi> which I most of all ſuſpected,
<pb facs="tcp:15002:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>and ſaw ſome cauſe to doubt, till <hi>PRAYER</hi> in concluſion did vndertake to perfect or perſwade the best. So that if the <hi>Forme</hi> for the plaineneſſe may paſſe without offence, the <hi>Matter</hi> for im<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>portance may perhaps deſerue a double and treble reading.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Matter</hi> indeed is <hi>TRAFFICK,</hi> I meane our freeborne <hi>Traffick,</hi> that Nurſe of <hi>IVSTICE</hi> which feedes vs all, and (heere handled <hi>ab Effectis,</hi>) containes thoſe very <hi>CVSTVMS</hi> for which the <hi>Schollers</hi> in all the <hi>Free-ſchooles,</hi> of our <hi>SOVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RAIGNES</hi> daily <hi>Tributes,</hi> haue ſo long beene ſubiect to bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and beating: and for which my ſelfe, of late ſo graciouſly chidden, was forſt (by ſpeciall commaund,) to ſpell againe my Letters, and con this <hi>PRIMER.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now be it what it may be, as your <hi>WISDOMS</hi> ſhall eſteeme, and as <hi>GOD</hi> ſhall giue ſucceſſe, (to whom the Glorie of <hi>All</hi> in <hi>All</hi> is due,) three principall reaſons haue moou'd me to preſent it to your LLL: view, in the names of All the reſt. The <hi>FIRST,</hi> beſides his <hi>knowledge</hi> and ſufficiencie of skill, by emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nencie and Place hath ſpeciall Experience to iudge of what I write. The <hi>SECOND,</hi> keepes the Keyes of all thoſe verie <hi>Ports</hi> that lymits out my Charge, for whoſe ſakes indeede reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proke Loue did instant me to write. And the <hi>THIRD</hi> was the meanes to make me first a <hi>Cuſtumer,</hi> when I had giuen it ouer and little thought vppon it. For theſe regards (I ſay) and tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble reſpects, (mine Ends beeing no wayes priuat, myne Intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons alwaies Loyall, diſclayming no mans Perſon, but Sinne and Diſhoneſtie,) I held it meeteſt and ſafest, to preſent my <hi>Selfe,</hi> and the Fruites of all my Vowes, to your LLL: mylde Cenſures and Protections. By whoſe ſpeciall Fauours, as I am but what I am, ſo I deſire but to be knowne</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your LLL: by ſeuerall Duties deuotedly bound</hi> Tho: Milles.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:3"/>
            <head>To the GRAVEST and GODLIE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VVISE <hi>in Higheſt Authority.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg> 
               <hi>Gentleman,</hi> a friend, and a louer of learning, comming into a Free-Schoole, where diuers young Schollers were lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Grammers, deſirous to feele how they thryude at their Bookes by ſome familiar Queſtion, demaunded, (their Huiſhers ſtanding by) <hi>VVhen an English is giuen to be made into Latine, whats first to be done?</hi> The aunſwer is eaſie: namelie, <hi>To ſeeke out the Principall Verbe:</hi> yet all ſtoode ſilent and halfe amazed, till (<note n="*" place="margin">The writer hereof, hauing ſpent the beſt of his youth in publique ſeruices at home and abroade, and deſirous at laſt to ſettle himſelfe in ſome ſtayd courſe of liuing; after the Treaty at <hi>Barwick</hi> 1586. caled <hi>Foedus arctioris amicitiae inter poten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſſimos. &amp;c.</hi> (which with the grace of God, the truth of his Title and his owne patience, was a meanes that brought his Maieſtie ſo quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and happily hether,) was by his Friendes perſwaded to take the charge vpon him of Cuſtumer of Sandwich and the Member-Ports in Kent, where he was borne, aſſuring him, that thereby he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> might doe God and his Country good ſeruice: vpon which motiue, hee vndertooke the ſame <hi>ſimply,</hi> and <hi>doubting no harme.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>one</hi>) at the laſt, (the Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion repeated, and he vrged to ſay, <hi>VVhat was to be done</hi>) replyed; <hi>No harme ſir I hope, at leaſt, that I wote of.</hi> Which the <hi>Gentleman</hi> ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in very good part, ſuſpecting rather ignorance in the Huiſhers, then want of wit in the Scholler, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted ſmyling.</p>
            <p>Moſt <hi>Reuerend,</hi> and <hi>Right Honourable,</hi> This Queſtion and Aunſwere, includeth the ſtate of all the Students in the Free-Schooles of <hi>our Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes Custumes,</hi> where ſuch as the Teachers be, ſuch are the Schollers. There is a reaſon for all thinges. And the reaſon heereof is not ſo much, for want of
<pb facs="tcp:15002:4"/>wit, in the Learners; <hi>To deale iuſtly betweene the Prince and the people,</hi> which in this kinde of Doctrine is the <hi>Principall Verbe,</hi> as in their angry and haſtie Huiſhers, who while the <hi>Graue-Maisters</hi> and <hi>Moderators</hi> of the Schooles, were diſtracted, and buſied in the ſtudy and practiſe of higheſt poynts of Learning, haue vſed no Method, but beating the Schollers.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui paria eſſe volunt peccata. Ipſique laborant</l>
               <l>Cum ventum ad verum eſt, Senſus moreſque repugnant,</l>
               <l>Atque (ipſa <hi>VTILITAS,</hi>) <hi>Iuſti</hi> prope mater &amp; <hi>Aequi.</hi>
               </l>
            </q>
            <q>That make all faults alike, yet they themſelues are dome, When Truth in queſtion falls, each finger ſeemes a thome, And (<hi>Profits</hi>-ſelfe) empaird, whence <hi>Iuſt</hi> &amp; <hi>Right</hi> ſhould come.</q>
            <p>Which kinde of Diſcipline diſcouraging all men, and driuing many good wits from the Schoole, to the ſecrete iniury of the whole Common-wealth; forcde me to my Booke, and as well as I could, to <hi>Analiſe</hi> my leſſon, meaning therby with the fore-ſaid playne Scholler, <hi>No harme at all.</hi> Such there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as it was, I did briefely ſet forth in a<note n="*" place="margin">The CVSTOMERS Apologie.</note> 
               <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> then following. The matter whereof partly drawne from mine owne patience and experience, &amp; partly obſerued and learned from others: the Forme vvas meerely mine owne, and had for my warrant the Rules of my Grammer.</p>
            <p>And ſince <hi>Thinges are then well done, when thinges are well taken;</hi> to cleare and acquite me from partiall clamor, and the ſinne of preſumtion; I ſhewd, That the Will applyant to Reaſon, was guiltleſſe of paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Nature ouer-borne appeales to Neceſsitie. <hi>Quae quod cogit, ipſa, ſolet vti<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> defendere.</hi> For hard in
<pb facs="tcp:15002:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>deede, and aboue meaſure extreame ſhould theyr caſes ſeeme, that ſtill ſubiect to beating, might ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bemoane themſelues, nor bee ſuffered to cry. And ſo much the rather, when as <hi>(ſo farre as I wot of)</hi> in all thoſe Complaints, there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing concluded nor included, at leaſt intended thereby, but a naturall Defence of an honeſt reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in that kind of Calling, which the Law it ſelfe in great wiſedome hath layde out, and reſerued <hi>For men of the beſt ſort onely,</hi> and a dutifull zeale to find out thereby <hi>The principall Verbe.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ Thus farre forth, &amp; in theſe very words, hauing ſometimes vndertaken a priuate Defence in a Cauſe of importance both publique and Generall, and finding our groanes &amp; heauy Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints are vaniſhed like ſounds, and valued but as <hi>Ecchoes</hi> in the * <hi>Deſerts</hi> and <hi>Playnes,</hi> neere the FORREST OF SHIFTS, and WILDERNES OF SIN. Which whilſt ſome went by, they heard not, ſome heard, but vnderſtood not, ſome few vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, regarded not, and none did pitty: I held it then beſt (like a barne ſo dingd that I durſt no longer griet) to ſup vp my griefes with ſilence.</p>
               <p>But when I perceiued, that though I ſate ſtill, the cauſe it ſelfe daily did grow worſe &amp; worſe: &amp; remembred withall my<note n="*" place="margin">Cuſtomers are ſworne at theyr firſt admiſsion, to doe their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uours to deale iuſtly between the Prince and the People.</note> vow to my Patron and Founder of our Schooles, at my firſt admiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: in diſcharge of my dutie, which in this reſpect I owe to my God, to my Prince and my Country, I once more reſolued to ſpeake with my penne, and examine all my former writings, not as by way of <hi>Geneſis</hi> to preſcribe a new Arte to our Graue &amp; Wiſe Maiſters, for that were preſumption in the higheſt degree: nor as by <hi>Analiſis</hi> to conteſt with the Doctrine and Method of our ſeuereſt Huiſhers, for that were but humour &amp; indeſcretion: but whilſt <hi>others</hi> of higher Formes,<note n="¶" place="margin">Learned Sir <hi>Henry Billingsley,</hi> ſometimes Cuſtomer of London.</note> and farre better learning diſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting theyr Schooles, remooued theyr ſeates to a ſurer ſtanding,<note n="¶" place="margin">Worthy Sir <hi>Thomas Ridgeway,</hi> Cuſtomer of Exeter and Dart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mouth. Nowe Treaſurer of Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</note> as a poore Scholler deſirous to learne and thriue at my Booke, to ſpell out my <hi>Primer</hi> by the very letters and poynts of my leſſon. That ſo redeeming the time, I might beſt giue way to the ſtreame of diſgraces in hope of better dayes now coming: remembring withall, that <hi>Errors</hi> haue no beeing but in abſence of <hi>Truth.</hi> And howſoeuer <hi>Errors</hi> paſt haue multiplyed themſelues, the Ages ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding muſt reforme as they may, &amp; as there is a reaſon, ſo God hath appointed a time for all things, for <hi>Dies dat conſilium.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>Conſidering therefore the reuolutions nowe paſt, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent diſpoſition of theſe our happy dayes, the<note n="*" place="margin">The KING.</note> 
                  <hi>Day-star</hi> beeing riſen, and the<note n="*" place="margin">The PRINCE.</note> 
                  <hi>Dawning</hi> in our eyes, reuiues our dull ſpirits, ads life to our hopes, and makes Vs breathe out yet this much &amp; ſay, that the time may come, when this hartie zeale of ours to our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraignes honour, and his Peoples happines, may be better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and deſerue not onely thanks and good words, but make all men confeſſe and acknowledge themſelues, as much indebted to theſe weake indeuours of ours, euen from an<note n="*" place="margin">Sandwich.</note> Out-Port in the Deſart, &amp; humble<note n="*" place="margin">Norton-Court.</note> Cottage of this Laud, as all their wealths are or can be made worth: And the Ages to come, find ſomthing at leaſt to muſe and to maruaile at ignorances paſt, when it ſhall plainely appeare by demonſtratiue reaſons, and no wandering Diſcourſe, that in poore Cuſtomers Truth was neuer <hi>Error,</hi> nor Vertue Vice, as the World hath beene told, and ſo long borne in hand. For can they but ſee, they ſhall learne to ſpell, &amp; by ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Letters, both reade and diſcerne (beſides other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tets,) that<note n="1" place="margin">CVSTVMERS.</note> 
                  <hi>Publicans</hi> and<note n="2" place="margin">SEARCHERS and WAITERS.</note> 
                  <hi>Sinners,</hi> are ſeuerall words, &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a diſtinction both of manners and men, and were it, or might it be that Docible Perſons were but ſuffered to learne, <hi>Publicans</hi> could &amp; would teach <hi>Sinners</hi> to be like themſelues: not <hi>Saints</hi> nor <hi>Hypocrites,</hi> but firſt humble Chriſtians, and then plaine honeſt men.</p>
               <q>
                  <hi>In my beginning therefore God be my ſpeede.</hi>
               </q>
               <q>A Iove principium Muſae Iouis omnia plena.</q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ GOD Alſufficient, <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> onely Wiſe, and eternally Iuſt,<note place="margin">Great A</note> without precedent or patterne, out of Confuſion firſt drew Perfection, and at the end of his Worke, delighted to behold that all he had made was ſo like himſelfe, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alde Bona,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding good.</p>
               <p>The laſt of all was MAN, the Image of himſelfe, his <hi>Micro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coſmus, Chiefe D'oeuure,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Little A.</note> Maiſter-peece, &amp; modell of Perfection. In whom, and by whom, he might contemplate, direct, &amp; make vſe of all the reſt. But pride by preſumption perſwading diſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, Man became ſeduced, and by <hi>the least part of his trust,</hi> bewraying his whole Corruption, in ſteed of bleſsing was wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily accurſt, both in him &amp; his, had not <hi>Wiſedome</hi> herſelfe, out of loue and affection ſo belayed his fall, that the Word which made all of nothing, was the meanes to reſtore all from nothing, and GOD became a MAN. A miracle of miracles, and myſterie to muſe on, but not to expreſſe: whereby the greateſt loſer, hath made the greateſt gaine.</p>
               <p>As the motiue of the Worke was the Creators onely Will, the meanes his Word, the way his Wiſedom, the meaſure <hi>Aequum et Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> bounds of his owne Iuſtice: So the abſolute perfection, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:15002:5"/>end of all, was his preſeruing and boundleſſe mercy, (the Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of <hi>Deitie,</hi>) for the Creature to admire on, as his Creators infinite honour, and owne eternall happines.</p>
               <p>Now, whatſoeuer <hi>Nature</hi> could afford, or <hi>Man</hi> thus reſtored was able to poſſeſſe, is Gods free gyft from all beginning. That as a Lord peramount, his honour &amp; ſeuice might iuſtly be known to all his Tennants by ſpeciall duties, and thankfull acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgements of their caſie Rents, and ſo rich a Fee-farme.</p>
               <p>The titles of his Tenures are RELIGION and IVSTICE, the one maintaines his peculiar honour and perſonall Rights, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, effects of <hi>Loue</hi> &amp; <hi>Loyalty,</hi> for his Tennants mutuall good: the Lawes, Cuſtomes and Doctrine whereof, pend by his Spirit, and drawne from the eſſence of heauenly <hi>Deitie,</hi> are ſo concurrent; that to perfect our happines, where both of theſe are not, there can be neither: and therefore Comparatiuely vſed in this our Leſſon, ſhal both ſanctifie our wits, bleſſe our endeuours, &amp; illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate each other.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Qui per alium facit, per ſemetipſum facit.</hi> Gods immediat<note n="1" place="margin">Prayers &amp; Thanksgiuin</note> Rents, God himſelfe expects and receiues at our hands, ſuch is our Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nure: the<note n="2" place="margin">Tythes and Tributes.</note> reſt he accepts, being faithfully payd to his Stewards and Vicegerents. In which reſpect we ſtand alſo bound to reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and admire the tranſcendent reſpects of Soueraigne ſublu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie in earthly States, by theyr <hi>Attributes</hi> &amp; <hi>Tributes,</hi> as GODS among men.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Preheminence.</hi> PReRoGaTiue.</note>The <hi>Attributes</hi> of power in earthly Princes, are their PREHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINENCE and their PREROGATIVE, (<hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Mercie</hi>) the two ſacred Titles of Diuine Soueraigntie: the one ſets forth the Dignities of their <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Places,</hi> the other tranſcends to the motions of their mindes.</p>
               <p>The firſt is that <hi>Storge,</hi> and naturall inclination to <hi>Equitie</hi> and <hi>Iustice,</hi> that diſtributing bread to the meaneſt of their Subiects, entendeth at leaſt that all ſhould enioy their <hi>Birthrights,</hi> to the generall Treaties of Entercouſe abroade, and Common Lavves at home, to grow vp thereby to liue to theyr ſeruice &amp; the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth.</p>
               <p>By the other, out of meere <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> it may well be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeme them, to ſtande gracious to ſome more then all the reſt, euen beyond the boundes of <hi>Iustice,</hi> and yet doe no wrong.</p>
               <p>The firſt ſhewes them but from their Seates of <hi>Iustice</hi> &amp; height of <hi>Diguities</hi> aboue other men.</p>
               <p>The latter beyond the Thrones of Kings, extolls their <hi>Perſons</hi> higher then themſelues, as more then the ſonnes of mortall men.</p>
               <p>Theſe then are no <hi>Synonimas</hi> (in our dymme ſights and vveake Conceits) but words of diſtinct reſpects, &amp; of Chiefeſt reuerence,<note place="margin">Cat' exochen.</note> the blending whereof, hath breadde in the World ſuch dangerous Contempts and Capitall Errors, as no Power but the Higheſt, no
<pb facs="tcp:15002:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>Wiſedome but the Graueſt, may or can reforme. To who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in all obedience wee proſtrately referre them. Onelie in the firſt wee ſpy the ſame forme of Caracters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Preheminence. PREROGATIUE.</hi> Whereof reade more in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of (Trafficke) hereafter.</note> as in the Alphabet of our Letters. But in the other, (beeing a <hi>Hyeroglificke</hi> aboue our reach or Learning) wee heare the full ſound of all thoſe vovvels, that giue life to our Mutes, &amp; muſt direct our ſpelling in the Title of our <hi>Tributes:</hi> the ſcope of Loyaltie, and nowe our ſpeciall Leſſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="¶" place="margin">Cuſtomers Creede &amp; Beleefe, and Articles of Religion.</note>Leauing therfore the Rights of <hi>Religion</hi> to thoſe learned Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, that both by life and doctrine, directing the way by <hi>Fayth</hi> and <hi>Good-workes</hi> how to winne Heauen, teach vs that <hi>Faith</hi> alone in the Action of ſauing, is the Cauſe of Saluation; but in the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſaued, both muſt concur together. And not to thoſe <hi>deſtruc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> Doctors,<note place="margin">Not Popiſh.</note> that to build vp theyr Church, blow vp Common-weales: and by Looſenes of lyfe, and Traditions of Men, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunce themſelues, rob GOD of his honour. Nor theſe <hi>distrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> Teachers,<note place="margin">Nor Preciſe.</note> that to Reforme our Church, diſturbe our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and prepoſterouſly propounding ſuch fancies of Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as no reaſon can reach to, nor themſelues expreſſe, preferring Sacrifice before Obedience, diſpence with <hi>Charitie</hi> to pleaſe ſelues,<note place="margin">But the Catholick, Apoſtolick, &amp; Chriſtian Fayth, now truely taught, freely profeſsed, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly defended, in the Churches of England, Scotland &amp; Ireland.</note> &amp; obtrude vpon GOD more then he requires. Aſſuring our ſelues, that to all who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his Spirit doth make Repentant, GOD by CHRIST, is and will be a moſt gracious GOD, and a louing Father. But GOD without CHRIST is a conſuming fire.</p>
               <p>This (I ſay) we leaue to thoſe ſacred Diuines that worke obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in Subiects by the rules of Conſcience; and admiring the bleſſednes of theſe our dayes, pray for our <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Prelates,</hi> &amp; all that vphold or haue but a will to further this our truly <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke</hi> and <hi>Christian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Decalogue of our Courts of Iuſtice, whereto Cuſtomers frame the Rules of their Ciuill lyfe and conuerſation in England.</note>¶ Leauing alſo the Duties of all our <hi>distributiue Iustice,</hi> to thoſe moſt Woorthy and moſt Honourable Perſons, that poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Courts, by MEVM and TVVM, diſcerne and decyde the Caſes and Queſtions of ſpeciall Right, and of generall Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, as well betweene Subiect and<note n="b" place="margin">1 Common-PLEAS.</note> Subiect, as the Soueraigne and his<note n="c" place="margin">2 Kings-BENCH, and Court of Wardes.</note> Vaſſalls, by the Lawes and Statutes, or peculiar Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, caſt in the<note n="d" place="margin">3 PARLIAMENT.</note> Mould of Wiſedome in our owne Land; or moderate Extreames by<note n="f" place="margin">4 CHAVNCERY, &amp; Court of Requeſts.</note> Conſcience among Men. And to the Graueſt &amp; Wiſeſt in<note n="g" place="margin">5 STAR-CHAMBER, &amp; Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell-Table.</note> higheſt Authoritie, that to maintaine the Good by cenſuring the Euill, <hi>Sic iraſcuntur, vt vitia tantu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> perimant ſeruatis hominibus, atque ita tractatis vt veri boni neceſſariò fiant: quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> damni antea dederiut, in reliqua vita reſarcire queant.</hi> And to thoſe Heroicall<note n="h" place="margin">6 The high Coneſtable and</note> Cenſors of merit and valour, that beeing moſt <hi>Noble</hi> themſelues, to decyde the Doubts, and determine the Queſtions of reputation &amp; worth in all the Degrees of our <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> Right, and <hi>Datiue</hi> Honour, ſo maintaine our Credits, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quum Praedia, Feuda et Poſſeſſiones, pactis et tranſactionibus obnoxia: Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris-Communis,
<pb facs="tcp:15002:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>et forenſibus procellis agitentur:</hi> NOBILITAS <hi>interea,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Earle-Marſhalls Court of CHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>VALRY.</note> 
                  <hi>ſolis Regibus beneficiaria, Inſtitutis heroicis, et familiaribus ita acquieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit.</hi> That</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Per proauos numerantur aui, ſemperque renata</l>
                  <l>Nobilitate virent, et prolem Fata ſequntur.</l>
                  <l>Continuum propria ſeruantia lege tenorem.</l>
               </q>
               <p>And to thoſe learned Ciuilians, that <hi>per Aequum et Bonum,</hi> ſo belay the publique peace of our<note n="k" place="margin">7 ADMIRALTIE.</note> Seas, and our<note n="l" place="margin">8 ARCHES.</note> Land, that by dooing vs Iuſtice, our Neighbours take no wrong.</p>
               <p>Theſe parts (I ſay) of diſtributiue <hi>Iustice,</hi> we gladly referre to thoſe worthy Iudges that ſit in our Courts, and by Law &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience protecting our<note n="a" place="margin">Matter.</note> 
                  <hi>Liuings,</hi> our<note n="c" place="margin">Place.</note> 
                  <hi>Liberties,</hi> our<note n="i" place="margin">Perſons.</note> 
                  <hi>Liues,</hi> our<note n="o" place="margin">Order.</note> 
                  <hi>Honour,</hi> &amp; our<note n="u" place="margin">End.</note> 
                  <hi>Peace;</hi> doe iuſtly deſerue all Grace fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraigne, and all loue at his handes. Theſe are the GRAVE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAISTERS &amp; Moderators of our Schooles,<note place="margin">Our <hi>Maiſters.</hi>
                  </note> that by the Rules of our Bookes, examine our Leſſons.</p>
               <p>The <hi>Prince</hi> hath his Courts apart, for<note n="m" place="margin">9 EXCHECKER.</note> 
                  <hi>Publique</hi> Reuenewes and<note n="n" place="margin">10 GREENECLOTH.</note> 
                  <hi>Priuate</hi> Expences: where Accountants are taught for the moſt part, by Court-Rowles &amp; Court-Rules, grounded on Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents, Examples, or elſe Diſcretion. Thoſe firſt are our <hi>Huiſhers.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Our <hi>Huſhiers.</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>The Comfort is great where Men dwell in houſes, whoſe foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation is layd on aſſured grounds. In which regard wee <hi>poore</hi>
                  <note n="p" place="margin">Cuſtomers.</note> 
                  <hi>Schollers,</hi> want words to expreſſe our Ioyes and Conceites, of the bleſsings of GOD in theſe our dayes, for the ſtayes of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> and <hi>distributiue Iuſtice.</hi> Were thoſe <hi>Patrons</hi> of Honour whom <hi>Mercury</hi> ſhould ſerue, by APOLLO but found out: &amp; the roofes of our <hi>Schooles</hi> made wind-tight and water-tight in the breaches &amp; wants of<note n="q" place="margin">Trafficke.</note> 
                  <hi>Commutatiue Right:</hi> We (I ſay) with all thoſe that ſerue in the<note n="r" place="margin">Staples.</note> Temples of Concord, and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Mynts.</note> Altars of Truth, would make verſes in prayſe of our PRINCES and PEERES, and ſing <hi>Alleluiah</hi> to the great GOD of Heauen.</p>
               <p>The Commutatiue part then that ſeemes moſt out of frame, now falling out, and fitted for our Leſſon, we are by our Letters to ſpel out the words that belong to the Titles of our PATRONS<note n="t" place="margin">Cuſtomes.</note>. <note n="w" place="margin">Subſidies</note>. <note n="x" place="margin">Tonnage and</note> 
                  <note n="z" place="margin">Pondage.</note>. Tributes. Wherin our mild <hi>Moderators</hi> vouchſafe to ſtand by vs, helpe our dym eye-ſights, ſupport our weake wits, &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect our ſhaking hands. And Chriſtes <g ref="char:cross">✚</g> be my ſpeede, and the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The Nature of all Things that conſiſt in Action, is beſt ſeen and valued by the eminencie of the Obiect whereon it workes, and End whereto it tends.</p>
               <p>The higheſt Obiect (next GOD and <hi>Religion,</hi>) is the Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie of our SOVERAIGNE, and Good of our Country, there beeing no Action more dutifull then to amplifie the honour of
<pb facs="tcp:15002:7"/>the <hi>One,</hi> and procure the proſperitie of the <hi>Other:</hi> nor any more odious, then wittingly or willingly to empayre the Meanes, mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually meant for the maintenaunce of Either.</p>
               <p>It followes then by conſequence, at all hands agreed on, that to maintaine the Princes Reuenewes, and to further the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie and peace of his People, is (or ought to be) the ſpeciall care of euery Mans beſt Endeuour.</p>
               <p>The Duties which GOD hath layd out, and for his honor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued, by the words of his Law were double onely, and of two ſeuerall kindes, daily <hi>Sacrifices</hi> and <hi>Oblations</hi> of Free-will. The one proceeding, from the ordinary Obſeruaunce that giues the formall diſtinction betweene the <hi>Creature</hi> and the CREATOR. The other demonſtrates that francknes of <hi>Loue</hi> and cheerefull <hi>Deuotion,</hi> that ought to proceede from the harts of his owne and peculiar People.</p>
               <p>Nowe that which <hi>Deitie</hi> demaunds by the Lawes of <hi>Religion,</hi> within his Church to be honored by, doth hold as a conſequence for earthly Princes within their Kingdoms to raiſe their Tributes by. Like Obiects, like Ends, <hi>Maieſtie,</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> by two ſorts of Duties, <hi>Neceſſitie</hi> and <hi>Free-will.</hi> The One muſt ſubſiſt, the Other cannot be bound. Giue therefore as vnto GOD himſelfe that which is GODS; ſo vnto <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that is due to <hi>Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus Cuſtomes that grow by <hi>Trafficke,</hi> are due to our KING, and are no ſmall nor idle Portions in the Body of his Reuenews. But as in <hi>Religion</hi> and the ſeruice of GOD, there is nothing hath more diſturbed the Conſcience, nor diſtracted Mens minds, then a miſvnderſtanding, and diuerſity in conceits, of the true ſence and vſe of the word (<hi>Church,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> wordes that are too generally taken: and ſo miſvnderſtoode.</note>) ſo fares it with Traffick about the Tearmes and vſe of <hi>Customes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For though <hi>Customes</hi> (in this kinde) doe currantly runne, and be vſually taken for all kinde of Duties that acrue to the King on things Barterable or Vendible, by way of Marchandiſe croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Seas, either Outward or Inward, (for from Port to Port both Land &amp; Seas are naturally free) yet it hath a peculiar ſence, a ſpeciall vſe and proper ſignification, implying eyther thoſe an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Staple-Rights,</hi> on Wooll, Wooll-fells, Tinne, Lead &amp; Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, &amp;c. called <hi>Great</hi> and <hi>Grand Customes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Grand CVSTOMS.</note> outward; or the three pence on the pound, payd onely by Strangers, by the name of <hi>Petty-Customes.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Petite CVSTOMS.</note>
               </p>
               <p>All Titles beſides (of this kind) howſoeuer they be called, or generally compriſed and ſtiled <hi>Customes,</hi> are notwithſtanding, diſtinguiſhed from them by ſpeciall Names,<note place="margin">Subſidies Tonnage and</note> and different vſes, as <hi>Subſidies,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Subſidies Pondage.</note> or <hi>Aydes.</hi> And thoſe alſo ſubdiuided into <hi>Tonnage</hi> &amp; <hi>Pondage.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The vſe and end of CVSTOMS.</note>The firſt (properly, indeede onely to be called Cuſtomes) by wiſedome layd out from all beginning, is <hi>Ius Coronae,</hi> an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance
<pb facs="tcp:15002:7"/>of the Crowne, the <hi>preemption</hi> in Trafficke, and <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection</hi> of Traffick, beeing two Eſſentiall partes of that perſonall <hi>Preeminence,</hi> and locall <hi>Dignitie,</hi> which fundamentally our Kings haue claimed, and for defence of the Kingdome, and ſafe paſſage at Seas, iuſtly may challenge. As conſiſting (to our Weake vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandings) of the chiefeſt Materialls our State affoords, to to draw in <hi>Bullion</hi> by.<note place="margin">Bullion. Staples. Mynts. Exchange. Weights &amp; Meaſure.</note> And in that reſpect holden for their <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificiall Mynes</hi> of Gold &amp; Siluer, to maintaine the Pulſes of our Soueraignes <hi>Mynts,</hi> whoſe <hi>Exchange</hi> of Money, as a Fountaine for abundance, ought to fixe and guide the true valuations of all Things beſides. For as the Standarts of all Weights &amp; Meaſures for generall Iuſtice, are the Soueraignes Treaſure and peculiar charge, &amp; the coyning of Monies theyr onely <hi>(Hoc age,)</hi> ſo their<note place="margin">Generall Iustice.</note> Coynage, a worke for Matter &amp; Forme of principall Worth, &amp; theyr <hi>Exchange</hi> a Myſterie of heauenly skill, by equalitie and proportions <hi>certaine</hi> and <hi>indifferent,</hi> are the Sterne and Compaſſe to ſteere all courſes right.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Vſe and End of the Subſidies of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage.</hi>
                  </note>The later called <hi>Subſidies,</hi> are offred vp at Parliaments, on things ſubiect to Reſtraints by Proclamations for ſpeciall Cauſes and different vſe, and in that regard giuen ſometimes but on this Thing, ſometimes but at that Port, and ſome-times <hi>Ad Tempus</hi> onelie. Though now for all Things, at all Ports, and for terme of our Soueraignes lyfe, as vrgent Neceſſity, or publique Vtilitie, for the Freedome of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and behoofe of the <hi>Ports</hi> haue ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to require; Due likewiſe in their kinds and turnes for reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prock Ends. The <hi>Body</hi> beeing by GOD and <hi>Nature,</hi> ſo bound to ſerue and maintaine the <hi>Head,</hi> as the <hi>Head</hi> is ordained to gouerne and defend all the <hi>Members.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Customes</hi> are thoſe artificiall duties that our Kings muſt haue, and Neceſſity hath layd on <hi>Trafficke</hi> by our <hi>Staple Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>merce,</hi> to ſupply theyr naturall defects, and wants of <hi>Bullion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Subſidies</hi> are thoſe naturall reſpects which <hi>Loue</hi> is deſirous and <hi>Loyaltie</hi> doth offer, by <hi>Trafficke</hi> to honour our Soueraignes by (beſides theyr auncient <hi>Customes,</hi>) that by all Meanes, and at all hands <hi>Maieſtie</hi> may be ſeene, and <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> ſubſiſt.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Titles of our Commutatiue Tributes, by the Lawes of our Schooles, the bounds of our Leſſons, and Alpha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet of our Letters. Yet is there a third, called <hi>Impoſtes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Impostes <hi>or Impoſitions.</hi>
                  </note> or <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions,</hi> whoſe Heteroclite vſe, and conuertible ſound, wee know not how to ſpell: for beeing but the <hi>Genus</hi> to the former two, &amp; held for a <hi>Species</hi> of ſome other Duty in our weake conceits, hath deceiued many.</p>
               <p>For whereas <hi>Maiestie</hi> muſt, may &amp; can but ſubſiſt; what <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> and <hi>Tythes</hi> are to GOD, the ſame are <hi>Customes</hi> &amp; <hi>Subſidies</hi> to his <hi>Lieuetenants.</hi> And beyond the bounds which Wiſedome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes for the practiſe of <hi>Truth,</hi> Diſcretion may hunt, but ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:15002:8"/>find nought ſaue <hi>Error.</hi> For what exccedes, is but <hi>Poperie</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and in Policie, deuices to diſturbe <hi>Common-weales.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What reſts then but this, that <hi>Omne minimum inimica Naturae,</hi> &amp; <hi>Omne nimium vertitur in vitium.</hi> Enough makes a feaſt, but abuſes marre all, whereof we muſt alſo ſpell ſome-thinges hereafter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Impoſtes</hi> then by the Rules of our Bookes, and Letters of our Leſſons, are eyther the <hi>Cuſtoms</hi> wee ſpoke of, and thoſe <hi>Cuſtoms Impoſitions,</hi> that to maintaine the Eſſence of Maieſtie, Neceſſitie found out: Or thoſe <hi>Subſidies</hi> afore-ſaid, that Marchants by <hi>Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke</hi> doe franckly and willingly <hi>impoſe</hi> vppon themſelues: or els in our <hi>Natura Breuium,</hi> no where to be found.</p>
               <p>But as <hi>Aliquid Boni propter <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>icinum Bonum,</hi> ſo <hi>Multum mali propter vicinum Malum.</hi> Our Neighbours ſower Grapes haue ſet our teeth on edge.<note place="margin">Italian Gouernments, and the Diſcords of the Netherlands.</note> For by their examples, drawne (as they call it) from their Princes <hi>Prerogatiues,</hi> but would ſay <hi>Preheminonce,</hi> if they vnderſtoode themſelues. <hi>Impoſitions</hi> are made Taxes vppon Marchandiſe, beſides the duties aboue-ſayde: not ſo much by Statutes or Treaties of Entercourſe, as by a kinde of diſcretion, which wanting place and vſe in the ſtudie of our Cuſtomes, haue likewiſe no part in the honourable ends thereby propounded and intended. For beeing as they are, Effects of vnknowne Cauſes, of Matter vncertaine, and of forme no wayes fitting the Mould of our free Commerce, all men refuſe to argue thereof, to define, to deuide, or to bring them into Queſtion. The rather for that, beeing in theyr nature irregular and litigious,<note place="margin">The Popes ambitious Taxes on our Clergy, impoueriſhing the Realme by exhauſting our Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, made our Kings draw on the Barrons warres, to ſupply theyr pouerty &amp; wants, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the People. Impoſitions doe but ayme at Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and the preſeruation of our Shypping by gueſſe.</note> they haue beene occaſions of much vnreſt and diſorders in former times, eſpecially in the firſt and ſecond ages of our Kings, till <hi>Magna Charta</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded ſuch griefes. And albeit the vſe of them ſince might happily ayme at the beating backe of ſome Forraine idle Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities, brought in and obtruded vpon vs by Strangers, to the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance of our Trafficke in Trades, &amp; decay of our Ports in Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riners and Shipping, which the wiſedome of our State muſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes maintaine: yet gathering withall vppon the naturall and free-borne Subiects, they repyne thereat, as men willing to obey, but not able to diſcerne betweene the diſpoſitions of States, and changes of Tymes,<note place="margin">The Ends of <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order of <hi>Trafficke.</hi>
                  </note> &amp; ſo is a ſpeciall ground of all our Diſorders. The Subiect ſtill appealing to the poſitiue Lawes of our owne free <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as their generall Inheritance, and Strangers vrging theyr <hi>Treaties</hi> and mutuall <hi>Contracts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Impoſts</hi> of diſcretion or ſtrayned <hi>Preheminance,</hi> (if wee terme them right) haue likewiſe begotten ſome other <hi>Impoſitions,</hi> of baſer Nature, and more dangerous Effects, whereby that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Word of Wiſedome, and higheſt power, (our Soueraignes <hi>Prerogatiue,</hi>) is vnreuerently proſtituted, and many wayes pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned. For, beeing ſometimes pleaſed, (as well may beſeeme them) out of meere loue and affection, in publique reſtraints, by
<pb facs="tcp:15002:8"/>ſpeciall fauours to make ſome of their Seruants more happy then their fellowes; the ſame by ſales and tranſactions, tranſmuted or transferred, is a meanes to make Subiects from hand to hand,<note place="margin">Wine, Beere, Coales, &amp;c. And whatſoeuer in this kinde is eyther ſolde or put ouer to a ſecond or third hand for Money.</note> to racke and <hi>impoſe,</hi> euen vpon &amp; among themſelues. When indeed and in truth, the <hi>(Grace)</hi> looſeth <hi>Beeing,</hi> both in Matter, Forme, and Vſe, vppon the firſt <hi>Exchange.</hi> For when Fauourites get ſuits vnfitting theyr Callings, or vſe them not themſelues: it is but Witcheraft and Sorcery that all ſuch intend,<note place="margin">Simones-Magi.</note> as by Leaſes or Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for priuate gaine, thinke PRINCES <hi>Prerogatiues,</hi> eyther vendible for Money, or ſubiect to Exchange. Such <hi>Impoſt-Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters</hi> Religion hath accurſt, theyr Money therefore and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, (without Repentance) muſt periſh both together.</p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Impoſts</hi> we take it, (vnder our <hi>Graue-Maiſters</hi> correction) are but Romiſh <hi>Peter-pence,</hi> and <hi>Italian-Inuentions,</hi> where theyr PRINCES <hi>Prehemirence,</hi> and forſt kinde of <hi>Dignities,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trafficke</hi> ill beholden to all ſuch Engliſh Gentlemen as trauailing for experience, make the <hi>Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> of Italy a fit precedent for the gouernment of England, vvhen they come home.</note> haue little other Subſiſtence: Beeing therfore but borrowed, they may well be ſent home. <hi>England</hi> was neuer any vaſſall to <hi>Rome,</hi> and hath or may haue (beeing but rightly vſed) enough of her owne.</p>
               <p>But <hi>ô fortunatos Anglos bona ſi ſua norint!</hi> For the Maieſtie of our <hi>Customes</hi> ſomtimes ſo admired, ſeeme now like Anticke <hi>Medalls,</hi> that reteyning but their ſound, haue loſt themſelues in theyr Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue and Vſe, both of Matter and Forme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Our Golden-Flees, the Trophee of the Houſe of Bu gundy.</note>Thus our <hi>Woolls,</hi> (ſome-times the wonder of the Worlde,) are now the <hi>Trophees</hi> of ſtrange Lands, and ſignes of our ſhame, and turned into Cloth, our Cloth into nothing; at leaſt nothing leſſe then <hi>Bullion.</hi> And the Rates vppon <hi>Wooll,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Our Cloth become confiſcable beyond Seas, or by ſpeciall fauour returnable vpon vs.</note> firſt grounded by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutes, layd on Cloth by <hi>Diſcretion,</hi> not iuſtly diſcerning the reaſon of our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> in the Vſe of the <hi>One,</hi> and End of the <hi>Other.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our baſeſt <hi>Fell-wooll</hi> of Shorlings, the refuſe of the reſt, and ſweepings of our <hi>Staples,</hi> (neuer vſed in Cloth,) is by our kindeſt<note n="*" place="margin">The Duch-Church at Sandwich, who flying the tyranny of Body and Conſcience at home, admitted to refreſh themſelues but with our Engliſh ayre, layd the firſt foundation of true making of Bayes, Sayes, &amp; Sarges there. (Trades neuer vnderſtoode of vs be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,) till abuſes elſwhere ouer-whelmed them with others, with an <hi>Impoſition</hi> that well-neere breakes theyr harts: yet hold they ſtill theyr firſt innocencie, and maintaine the credite of that Townes-Seale, both for Number, Weight, and Meaſure, in all parts of the World.</note> Neighbours, in a new kinde of Drapery, made the glorie of our <hi>Wolls,</hi> and credite of our King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and might be made a Patterne to reforme all our Clothing, and recouer our <hi>Bullion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Pells</hi> &amp; our <hi>Leather</hi> forſake vs by Licenſes. GOD knowes why, where, how or whether, but without returne of <hi>Bullion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Tyn</hi> and our <hi>Leade,</hi> ſo lately well recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, ſeemes now againe layd vp in Huxters hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and might haue beene a ſure and ſpeciall helpe to haue drawne in <hi>Bullion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Our <hi>Pettit-Cuſtoms,</hi> onely ſeeme ſtill to holde their owne,<note place="margin">Lex Mercatoria.</note> but with vncertaine <hi>Bya<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> ſince <hi>Lex Mercatoria</hi> became obſolete, and to vs vnknowne.</p>
               <p>In ſteede of all which, our <hi>Returnes</hi> (for the moſt part) beeing but <hi>Silks</hi> and <hi>Tabacco,</hi> Bells or Bables, of things <hi>needleſſe</hi> or <hi>boote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:9"/>doe ſhew how Strangers for better wares, can fat vs vp with pryde, or fodder vs with folly.</p>
               <p>Our <hi>Subſidies</hi> that ſometimes were ſo fewe, ſo eaſie, ſo louing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offred, ſo graciouſly accepted, and ſo willingly payde, as the <hi>Customes</hi> haue fayled, are become the Subiects of <hi>Extremitie,</hi> euen to the tything of our ſmalleſt Mynt and Comin. And our ſweet <hi>Nurſe</hi> and <hi>Miſtreſſe,</hi> TRAFFICK, diſtempered and diſtreſt with dangerous fits of a hot burning Feauer. Not farre from Frenſie; which wee poore <hi>Schollers</hi> cannot but ſee, and (what ere betyde vs) bewayle and lament; and before our <hi>Grauest</hi> and <hi>Wiſest Phiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians,</hi> proſtrate our ſelues for remedy. And I among the reſt, as the <hi>Apothecaries Boy,</hi> that for bringing but one<note n="*" place="margin">The Caution writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> againſt the Farming out of <hi>Subſidies</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Cuſtomes.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Pill</hi> to preuent the laſt acceſſe, was ſo ſhent for my labour. The <hi>Symptome</hi> and <hi>Cryſis</hi> of whoſe diſeaſe will beſt appeare in our Leſſon nowe fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The faſhion and face of our <hi>Customes</hi> beeing thus layd open, theyr Vſe by practiſe but once made knowne; would enflame the world with admiration and loue of the ſpeciall Bleſſings &amp; Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of our Land; the Zeale whereof onely hath preuented all our Studies, almoſt conſumde our ſelues, and yet is the motiue of all our beſt Endeuours.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Customes</hi> therefore and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> both depending on <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as Effects that riſe and fall with theyr efficient Cauſe: the rayſing of <hi>Trafficke</hi> like Hony in Hyues, muſt needes increaſe eyther.</p>
               <p>TRAFFICKE! O the compaſſe and profunditie of this one &amp; onely word <hi>(Trafficke,)</hi> more fit for <hi>Wiſedome</hi> to ſtudy, and <hi>Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence</hi> to vtter, then our weake braynes to ſpell. In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard we cannot but bewayle the loſſe and want of thoſe worthy Wits of older tymes, that to tune the whole World, wrote Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumes on this Theme.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">SIBILLA CVMANA, ſhe wrot 9. Bookes, whereof 6. ſhe burnt, and ſold the other 3. to <hi>Tarquine</hi> for the price ſhe offred them all at firſt.</note>The three Bookes of SIBILLA, ſo well preſerued, ſo deerely bought, and carfully kept by <hi>Tarquine</hi> the <hi>Elder,</hi> are long ſince by <hi>Stillico</hi> that Traytor, blowne vp, burnt and gone.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Ne tantùm Patrijs ſaun et Proditor Armis,</l>
                  <l>Sancta <hi>SYBILLIN ae</hi> fata cremauit Opis.</l>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">ARISTOTLS abſtruſe Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy, to ALEXANDER the great, <hi>Horis matutinis in Gymnaſio Lyceo.</hi>
                  </note>But, ô, thoſe <hi>Acroamata,</hi> and pryuate Inſtructions of kingly Doctrine! ſo grauely diſcuſſed, ſo attentiuely heard, and richlie rewarded with Talents of Gold, are eyther forgotten, beyond our hearing, or out of our reach.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Card <hi>Poole</hi> ſpent abooue 2000. crownes in ſending to the Lybra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of <hi>Cracou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>a</hi> in <hi>Poland</hi> about it. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap> Sturm: Epiſt: lib:</hi> 1.</note>And <hi>Tully De Republica.</hi> A Booke able to make a Wiſe-man in one dayes reading, (as ſome beleeue and write) ſo carefullie ſought for, both farre and neere by our late <hi>Cardinall Poole,</hi> hath not yet been ſeene, except the <hi>Amalihean <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>atican</hi> of our newe<note n="o" place="margin">Sir <hi>Tho: Bodleyes</hi> Library at Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forde.</note> TARQVINIVS PRISCVS haue happily found it out, whoſe care, coſt, and loue to Learning, in the Kingdom of the <hi>Muſes,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>deſerues a Golden Crowne: yet this is our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort, that the light they ſaw by, was but beames of this <hi>Sunne,</hi> their <hi>Enthouſiaſme,</hi> but motions of this <hi>Good Spirit,</hi> and their cleereſt water fet from the ſtreames of this flowing <hi>Fountaine,</hi> that runnes ſo franckly, and may ſerue our Turne.</p>
               <p>For TRAFFICKE is but a free Bartering, or buying &amp; ſelling of 1 Vendible Wares. At 2 Markets co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient. By 3 Marchants, Subiects, or Strangers. According to the 4 Rules of Reciprocke Commerce. Generally intending 5 Honour to Princes, and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperitie to Common-wealthes.</p>
               <p>And here at the firſt view appeare all our fiue Vowells, in fiue Wordes, that teach vs all to ſpell, and make vs all to ſpeake; to wit, a MATTER, as <hi>Vendible Wares.</hi> e PLACE, <hi>Markets conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient.</hi> i PERSONS, <hi>Marchants, Subiects</hi> or <hi>Strangers.</hi> o ORDER, <hi>Rules of Reciprocke Commerce.</hi> And u END, <hi>Honour to Princes,</hi> and <hi>Proſperitie to</hi> v <hi>Common</hi>-v-<hi>wealthes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt wee call<note n="a." place="margin">¶ MATTER, muſt be vendible.</note> The ſecond ſtands for<note n="e." place="margin">¶ PLACE conuenient for Marts and Markets.</note> The third<note n="i." place="margin">¶ PERSONS, fit to Traffick.</note> The fourth is<note n="o." place="margin">¶ ORDER in Commerce.</note> The fift ſtands for<note n="u." place="margin">The KING</note> And (<note n="u." place="margin">PRINCE.</note> SIRS.) And<note n="u." place="margin">The COVNSAILE.</note> 
                  <hi>My Lords.</hi>
                  <note n="w." place="margin">The Common-wealth.</note> 
                  <hi>And all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Heere were fit ſtaying to admire on the Maieſtie of thoſe two wordes of Power, PReHeMiNeNS and PReRoGaTiue.<note place="margin">e. i.</note> Whereof the firſt hath two of our Vowels for PERSONS and PLACE, but the laſt contaynes them all.<note place="margin">a. e. i. o. u:</note> But wee muſt not play too much with the beauty of thoſe Letters: Let vs fall to our Bookes, and ſpell out our Leſſon.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="a." place="margin">¶ MATTER, muſt be vendible.</note>¶ In the condition of the <hi>Matter</hi> layde out for <hi>Trafficke,</hi> what euer it be, <hi>Goodnes</hi> more or leſſe makes it firſt Vendible, as reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the <hi>goodnes</hi> onely, and ſo fit for Trades.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="e." place="margin">¶ PLACE conuenient for Marts and Markers.</note>¶ In the <hi>Places,</hi> conueniencie at home or abroade; eaſineſſe of acceſſe by Sea or by Land, &amp; freedome with ſafetie: for <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> and <hi>Perſons</hi> is onely regarded in all Marts and Markets.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="i." place="margin">¶ PERSONS, fit to Traffick.</note>¶ In the qualitie of Marchants <hi>Perſons</hi> whoſoeuer they be, <hi>Subiect</hi> or <hi>Stranger, Loyaltie</hi> and <hi>Alliance</hi> onely makes their <hi>Traffick</hi> avowed. For with knowne Traytors, or open Enemies, the Law admits no Commerce.</p>
               <p>
                  <note n="o." place="margin">¶ ORDER in Commerce.</note>¶ The beſt Rules for <hi>Order</hi> to direct <hi>Trafficke</hi> by, are thoſe that beeing preciſely ſquared out, to the <hi>Generalitie, Certaintie,</hi> and <hi>Indifferencie</hi> of the <hi>Lawes</hi> of our Land, and forraine <hi>Contracts,</hi> ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit no particular, partiall, nor doubtfull deceit, iniury, nor di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbance to <hi>Matter, Perſons,</hi> nor <hi>Place.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note n="u." place="margin">¶ END of Trafficke.</note>¶ The <hi>End</hi> of all <hi>Trafficke,</hi> is <hi>Honour</hi> to Princes, and <hi>Proſperity</hi> to their Kingdoms; whoſe policie and gouernment, religious and Iuſt, muſt needes be formed to their Patterne DEITIE, by the <hi>Obiect</hi> of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> and end in <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But all Goodnes is needfull: <hi>Trafficke</hi> therfore in regard of the Vſe of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> muſt needes be generall. For looke what the
<pb facs="tcp:15002:10"/>Soule is to the outward Actions of the Body, in ordering each Member, ſo as Nature finds fit for the good of the whole <hi>Man:</hi> ſuch is <hi>Trafficke,</hi> in diſpoſing Myſteries &amp; Trades, to the behoofe of the whole <hi>Common-wealth.</hi> A conſideration in no part of Ciuill Gouernment to be neglected, much leſſe in this great <hi>Cauſe</hi> of <hi>Customes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>GOODNES therefore, as the life of the Soule, to perfect our <hi>Trafficke,</hi> both in <hi>Matter, Place, Perſons, Order</hi> &amp; <hi>End,</hi> is the ſcope of our Studie, and length of our Leſſons. That in <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as in all things, it may at laſt appeare, that <hi>Finis coronat Opus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Customes</hi> from <hi>Trafficke</hi> haue their firſt Eſſens &amp; beeing, and by it increaſe, to the <hi>Honour</hi> of Princes, and <hi>Proſperitie</hi> of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-weales. For <hi>Trafficke</hi> then it is that we <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> contend, &amp; ſtand bound to conteſt what euer betyde vs, vntill ſhee be relie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for our Leſſon, let vs play the <hi>good Schollers,</hi> and ply our Bookes well, to ſpell out <hi>Goodnes,</hi> that ſome <hi>Good-Man</hi> at laſt, may get vs leaue to play.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <q>¶ In regimine Ciuitatis. In Republica gubernanda, et in Orbis Imperio,<note place="margin">Euſebius.</note> minimum eſt quod poſſunt homines: In Cauſa vèrò Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gionis multo minus. Magna, Magnus perficit DE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S.</q>
               <p>He whoſe onely <hi>will,</hi> and abſolute <hi>Power</hi> could worke ſo well, that all hee made became exceeding <hi>Good,</hi> to his owne eternall Glory, and Mans immortall Bliſſe: GOD, I ſay GOD, I meane, &amp; GOD the third time, though ONCE for all. Whom onelie to know, is euerlaſting Life, and Ioy but to heare and make menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of his Name, beeing a law to himſelfe; of his owne Perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, doth likewiſe perfect all he <hi>wills</hi> or <hi>doth.</hi> His <hi>Goodnes</hi> beeing the Forme of all thinges, from which to ſwarue is to returne to Nothing, and which in him as the Fountaine we muſt admire, &amp; moſt affect and deſire in our ſelues.</p>
               <p>GOODNES then is the glorious center of DEITIE it ſelfe, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence all Circumferences both in Heauen and Earth, deriue not onely Eſſence, but happines in <hi>Beeing.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>From hence it is, that out of Learning and Zeale to Religious Rights, ſome godly-diſpoſed, haue ſeemed to obſerue a kind of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and free Commerce, betweene the <hi>Throne</hi> of Heauen, and the <hi>Church</hi> vpon Earth, by Doctrine &amp; Prayer for the vſe of <hi>Goodnes.</hi> All heauenly Inſpirings downeward, and all holie De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires vpwards, beeing as <hi>Angels</hi> or <hi>Marchants,</hi> betweene GOD and vs. That as his Doctrine doth teach vs our ſupreame <hi>Truth:</hi> ſo our Prayers might confeſſe him our ſoueraigne <hi>Good.</hi> But this height and depth of <hi>Goodnes</hi> we leaue to Diuines. The length &amp; breadth thereof, muſt lay forth our Leſſon, by giuing GOD his
<pb facs="tcp:15002:10"/>Honour, and our Soueraigne KING his Right. For <hi>Caelum Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lorum ſibi ipſi aſſumens, Terram dedit ſilijs hominum.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>As therefore at firſt we prayde God for our ſpeede,</l>
                  <l>So now in Goodnes, God graunt we proceede.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>Tu mihi ſumme Opifex rerum Cor fingitio purum</l>
                  <l>Et Recti inſpira renouatum pectore amorem.</l>
                  <l>Os mihi tute aperi. Tu dirige labra loquentis</l>
                  <l>Vt Tibi promeritae perſoluant laudis honores.</l>
               </q>
               <p>¶ We haue ſpeld already how our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies</hi> liue &amp; die with <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as Effects that follow theyr Efficient Cauſe. In which reſpect, firſt <hi>Trades</hi> and <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> muſt be ſought for, made of, and at all hands nouriſht. Then <hi>Marchants</hi> of all ſorts, muſt be kindly entreated, and by freedome encouraged in euery Common-wealth.</p>
               <p>All <hi>Trafficke</hi> is either <hi>Outward</hi> and <hi>Inward,</hi> of Things bredde at home, or ſet from abroad: and three things there are, that by the Spirit of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> giues it three degrees of lyfe, and thrice-happy beeing. Viz. <hi>Commodities, Money,</hi> and <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The firſt, as the BODY, vphelde the World in the infancie of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by bartering Good-things for Good-things,<note place="margin">Commodities.</note> to ſupply Neceſſities, till <hi>Fraude</hi> came in.</p>
               <p>The ſecond,<note place="margin">Money.</note> as the SOVLE in the <hi>Body,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Olim. Cum non eſset Monetae vſus, nec aliud Merx, aliud pretium dicereter: pro temporu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> rerum<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ratione, vtilia vtilibus permuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant bomines. Sed ob difficultatem contrabentium electa eſt Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teria, cuius publica et perpetua eſtimatio, premutationum diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatibus aequabilitate quantitatis ſubueniret.</note> beeing a weight of ſupreame woorth, to maintaine Equalitie, and preuent Aduantage by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſent or Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, firſt made Good-thinges ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible.</p>
               <p>The third, as the SPIRIT in the <hi>Soule,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Exchange.</note> is ſeated euery where in the Soueraignes owne boſome, to direct and controll by iuſt proportions of length and breadth, weight &amp; content, the truth, worth, and vſe of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> both in Money, and all Things els.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kata panta. Regula Veritatis.</note>The firſt, whilſt <hi>Goodnes</hi> in plaine dealing lay open to all like, knew not the Titles of Kings nor Kingdomes.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kat' auto. Regula Iuſtitiae.</note>The ſecond, is the right hand of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> which crowning Kings, firſt layde the foundation of that preheminent Dignitie, that ſhewes the difference and diſtinction of Soueraignes and Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.<note place="margin">Ius monetae proprium eſt Principis et inter Regalia Magna cenſetur.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Kath' olou Proton. Regula ſapientiae vel ordinis.</note>The third, is that forme of <hi>Maiestie,</hi> and tranſcendent Power, that of Mortall-Men, makes Gods on Earth.</p>
               <p>Thus in <hi>Trafficke, Commodities</hi> both Barterable and Vendible, by Trades and Myſteries are layd out for Subiects.<note place="margin">Poſt ipſam Legem nil aeque vtile eſt ac neceſsariu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Reipub: vt Nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vſus. Proinde Grecis <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos</hi> merito appellatur. Quaſi dicas gubernandi Regula. Vel gubernaculum.</note> 
                  <hi>Money</hi> as the <hi>weight</hi> to value the woorth, and <hi>Exchange</hi> the <hi>Meaſure,</hi> to ſette forth the vſe of <hi>Goodnes</hi> by, belongs onely to PRINCES, the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Miniſters of heauenly Iuſtice; Each ſupporting other by mutuall ſupplyes for Reciprocke Endes. The PRINCE graciouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:15002:11"/>beholding the <hi>proſperity</hi> and <hi>wealth</hi> of his loyall <hi>Subiects,</hi> as the onely Mirror of his owne Greatnes and Honor. And the <hi>Subiects</hi> religiouſly admiring the <hi>Maiestie</hi> of their <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> as the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Obiect of their <hi>Welfare</hi> and <hi>Good.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And thus it appeares by the courſe of our ſpelling, ſet poynts of our Leſſon, &amp; lynes of this our <hi>Primer.</hi> That our Kings Trade is <hi>Coyning,</hi> and his Myſterie is <hi>Exchange.</hi> His<note n="*" place="margin">The KINGS <hi>Proprium</hi> and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar <hi>Right.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Right</hi> therefore, <hi>vni, ſoli, et ſemper.</hi> By the rules of all <hi>Truth,</hi> all <hi>Iustice</hi> and all <hi>Order</hi> muſt be Gold and Siluer, Materialls of <hi>Bullion.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ The motyue of this worke, was a naturall defence of poore deſpiſed and contemned <hi>Customers;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The motyue of this ALPHA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BET, and mayne dryft of this PRIMER.</note> by whoſe diſgrace the <hi>King</hi> receiues ſuch loſſe, and the <hi>State</hi> more wrong. But the mayne dryft &amp; Scope of all, is an orderly aduancing of our Soueraignes Reuenewes in his duties of Cuſtomes, that ſo many haue vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, and ſo few haue ſet forward. Wherein all that hath beene ſaid, might paſſe but for conceit, and contemplatiue diſcourſe, without the hand of ſome Miniſteriall function.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Customes</hi> therefore beeing Effects of that great Cauſe vvhoſe Actions are conuerſant about no meaner Obiects then the Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes <hi>Honour,</hi> and Subiects <hi>happineſſe,</hi> requires Collectors of choyſe reſpect, and abſolute truſt: Men truly Religious and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt in deede, as <hi>Customers</hi> are euery way entended to be.</p>
               <p>And ſuch were they ſome-times reputed, till Neglect in theyr Choyce, and Contempt of theyr Perſons, made <hi>Ielouſie</hi> begin to ſuſpect their endeuours, whilſt <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Impudencie</hi> in coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce and maintenaunce ſupplanted their Credites. Firſt by <hi>Controllers,</hi> then <hi>Superuiſors,</hi> and laſtly by <hi>Farmers,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> beſides <hi>Searchers</hi> and <hi>Wayters</hi> God knowes how many.</p>
               <p>I come therefore now to ſpeake of that Function which vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lying the charge of ſo great a truſt, none ſhould obtrude on at aduenture, or vndertake in ieſt, but ſuch as Nature hath fitted, &amp; Authoritie admitted in lawfull manner. For how-ſoeuer the Name of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> ſeeme now out of fauour, as the Obiects of Diſgrace, and publique Slaunder; the curious eye of the Lawe (ſtill conſtant in his choyce,<note place="margin">The <hi>Customers</hi> onely knowne to the Lawe.</note>) call them kindly by their Names, and culls them all as curiouſly forth, (as Shriefes in their Shieres) <q>
                     <hi>from among the beſt and moſt ſufficient, that Wiſedome can find,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The intention of the Lawe in chooſing <hi>Customers.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>or choyce affoord,</hi> as men moſt fit to attend vpon <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and in collecting <hi>Customes,</hi> moſt likely of all others, <hi>To deals iuſtly betweene the Prince and People.</hi>
                  </q> Giue therefore cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, collect vprightly, and aunſwere truly, as vnto GOD him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, all his due honour, in <hi>Oblations</hi> and <hi>Tythes:</hi> ſo to our KING, all his due <hi>homages,</hi> in the Rights of his <hi>Customes,</hi> and loyall <hi>Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes. <hi>Deale (I ſay) iuſtly betweene the Prince and the People.</hi>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:11"/>HOC OPVS, HIC LABOR EST.</q>
               <p>This is the <hi>Dyapazon</hi> of all our <hi>Muſicke,</hi> and full compaſſe of that Song wherein each muſt hold apart; heere therefore pauſe a while, that all may ſing together.</p>
               <p>For great hath beene the care from time to time, &amp; the inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions ſundry, that haue beene vndertaken, for the aduauncing, collecting, &amp; true aunſwering, of all ſuch duties as grow in this kind. But as in the State of a naturall Body, thoſe diſeaſes proue of moſt dangerous conſequence, that are of longeſt breeding, &amp; furtheſt from cure, whoſe pulſe is neuer felt, nor Symptoma knowne; ſo hath it long fared with this Argument of <hi>Customes.</hi> Wherein ſometimes about the Cauſe it ſelfe, <hi>(Trafficke)</hi> vvhether free-borne or no, then about the <hi>Matter,</hi> without difference or diſtinction of <hi>Art</hi> or <hi>Nature, Outward</hi> or <hi>Inward, Abundance</hi> or <hi>Want, Dutie</hi> or <hi>Free-will.</hi> And laſtly about the Forme of theyr or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly directing, collecting, and true anſwering how to ſtoppe the courſe of <hi>Errors,</hi> and currant of <hi>Abuſes,</hi> is become the greateſt pretended care at leaſt and moſt ſerious Queſtion.</p>
               <p>For information and Reformation whereof, how-ſoeuer the Conſcience of my Calling vnder his ſacred <hi>Maiestie,</hi> &amp; ſpeciall dutie beſides, as his Highneſſe ſworne Seruaunt, haue ſingled <hi>me</hi> forth, and preſt <hi>me</hi> ſtill forward, by one occaſion or other. <hi>Quo fato neſcio, ſed non ſine Numine,</hi> as my hope and comfort is, firſt by<note n="1" place="margin">Againſt Informers of all ſorts.</note> 
                  <hi>A Generall Apollogie:</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a ſecond<note n="2" place="margin">Againſt priuate Societies.</note> 
                  <hi>Replyes,</hi> &amp;<note n="3" place="margin">A Treatiſe worth the reading.</note> 
                  <hi>The true vſe of Port Bands:</hi> &amp; laſtly, <hi>A Priuate</hi>
                  <note n="4" place="margin">The Satisfaction of the offence conceiued againſt that <hi>Caution,</hi> was the occaſion of caſting all the reſt into this new Mowld, called, 5 <hi>The Cuſtomers</hi> ALPHABET &amp; PRIMER.</note> 
                  <hi>Caution,</hi> againſt the Farming out of <hi>Subſidies,</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Customes,</hi> to preſume thus with my penne, but to wiſh and further; I euer concluded that none but the <hi>Graueſt</hi> and <hi>Wiſest</hi> in higheſt Authoritie, might promiſe and performe it: Before whom now beeing ſo lately commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſpeake, I may not, I cannot, I dare not hold my peace.</p>
               <p>All humble reſpect of Dutie therefore, &amp; proſtrate Reuerence premiſed, I proceede with my Leſſon, and build on our Defence vpon my firſt Religious and reaſonable grounds.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>RELIGION and IVSTICE, are the fundamentall ſtayes of all States and Kingdoms, the one by ſanctifying, the other by aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the perpetuities of all tranquilitie of Minds and earthly Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. <hi>Iustice</hi> beeing <hi>Diſtributiue</hi> and <hi>Commutatiue;</hi> the <hi>Commuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue</hi> part includeth <hi>Trafficke.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>There was a time when the Chriſtian world was all ſet on fire, deuided by Diſputes, and diſtracted in Opinions,<note place="margin">The true Catholick and Chriſtian Religion, as ſoundly taught, &amp; as freely profeſſed in England, Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land and Ireland at this day, as in any priuate or publicke part of the World.</note> about the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicke-Church,</hi> and ſome poynts of <hi>Truth</hi> in the doctrine of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion:</hi> But the GOD of Heauen be praiſed, it hath found the beſt footing in theſe our dayes &amp; Kingdoms that the world doth affoord, and his hand in our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and <hi>his,</hi> foreuer vphold it.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <note place="margin">Vppon the compounding of the Diſcordes in the Netherlands.</note>The like ſeemes now (I ſay, euen now) to offer it ſelfe about the Vſe &amp; Ends of our free-borne <hi>Trafficke,</hi> that Nurſe of Iuſtice which feedes vs <hi>All.</hi> The priuate peruerting of whoſe generall Intention to publicke <hi>Good,</hi> hath much diſturbed our ſpeciall Bliſſe, and giues occaſion of this ALPHABETOR PRIMER.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Trafficke</hi> then, beeing the hand that layes out all men theyr Worke, prouides all men theyr Foode, and payes all men theyr Fees, ought at all handes to be ſeriouſly ſupported, that ſo ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports vs all; and her willing Diſturbers, and witting Peruerters, held as Enemies to <hi>Order,</hi> that is to ſay, to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Nature.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſince in all Actions, the ſafeſt path to walke in, and ſureſt rule to guide our ſelues by, is to follow <hi>Nature,</hi> the patterne layd out by the GOD of <hi>Order:</hi> the way from <hi>Error</hi> to <hi>Truth,</hi> &amp; from <hi>Confuſion</hi> to <hi>Perfection,</hi> muſt be by proportions, vntill we come to that <hi>End,</hi> which is able and ſufficient to perfect and preſerue all our worldly happines. <hi>Meaſure</hi> therefore muſt ſit at the Sterne, and by ſteddy proportions, cunne and ſteere this our Shippe of <hi>Trafficke</hi> thorow all the ſtormes of Extremities and dangers of Shyfts, to our long-deſired Port.</p>
               <p>As the beauty of Nature is Order, ſo the way to Order is Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber more or leſſe, to auoyde the Rocks and Sands of <hi>Exceſſe</hi> and <hi>Defect. <hi>Exchange</hi>
                  </hi> therefore without all exceptions, muſt lay the foundation, and abſolute ground of all our Endeuours, to this intended Redreſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The Writer heereof, alluding to his owne trouble for the <hi>Caution</hi> hee wrote againſt the Farming out of <hi>Subſidies,</hi> vnder the name of <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,</hi> ſets forth withall a true <hi>Idea</hi> of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by fayning a Shyppe (called the <hi>Harry-Bonaduenture,</hi>) fraught with pitch, tarre, maſtes, ſalt and oyle, and good ſtore of <hi>Bullion:</hi> that after a long voyage, in her returne homewards to the Iland of <hi>Exchange,</hi> meetes with a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous ſtorme in the Narrow-Seas, and doubting the <hi>Geodyn-ſands,</hi> falls in with the Forelands, caſts Ankor in the Downes, and there ryding all Windes to death, puts in at laſt to <hi>Sandwich-Hauen.</hi> Where finding neither Staple nor Staple-wares, (ſometimes held there, and ſithence at <hi>Canterbury</hi> adioyning) of Fleece-wooll, Broad-clothes, Tyn, Lead, nor Leather. &amp;c barters her Commodities for Bayes, Sayes, and other Duch newe Drapery there. And in Exchange for her Bullion, beſpeakes Kentiſh Broade-clothes againſt her next re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne: Prouided, they be made &amp; warranted by the Rules of <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich</hi> Bayes, and Seale of that Towne onely, and none other.</note>
                  <hi>Exchange!</hi> haue we ſpyde out <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change?</hi> Then haile Maiſters, Marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and Mates at all hands: Call vp our loyall Marchants, true Patriots, Enterlopers and all, and be of good cheere. Belay well the Bowlyne, keepe your tacklins tight and ſure. Aloofe aloofe with the Maine for feare of the <hi>Goodwines.</hi> I ſeeme to ſee our Ilande, for the Fore-lands ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare. CASTOR and POLLVX co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming both together, did boade vs good-lucke. Our Barke is ſtrong e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to beare out her leakes. Our Loade-ſtone proues good, and our Compaſſe is true, therefore aloofe (I ſay) with the Maine, by this Cape of <hi>Good-hope,</hi> to the Harbor of Safetie, and Hauen of all our Reſt. For <hi>Reliquis tantum Sinus eſt et Statio malefida Carinis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now, all thinges conſiſt of Matter and Forme, <hi>et Forma dat eſſe rei:</hi> the Matter beeing Weight, and Meaſure the Forme, are fitted and eſteemed by their <hi>End</hi> and <hi>Obiect,</hi> GOODNES. All <hi>Goodnes</hi> is eyther by Nature or by Art. And as in <hi>Goodnes</hi> there is
<pb facs="tcp:15002:12"/>a proportion to fit with the <hi>Matter</hi> wherein it conſiſteth:<note place="margin">Omnis Forma infunditur ſecundum meritum Materiae.</note> So in <hi>Trades,</hi> the bleſſing of GOD by Nature, and the benefit of Indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry by Art, is more or leſſe admired, to the ſpeciall reputation &amp; profit of thoſe <hi>Perſons,</hi> and thoſe <hi>Places</hi> that firſt affoord them.</p>
               <p>According to theſe grounds of the three things in <hi>Trafficke</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore layd downe, as <hi>Money</hi> for the Matter, a Weight of greateſt worth, and for the Forme, a worke of royall eſteeme: So <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> a Meaſure of rareſt perfection, and Myſtery of heauenlie skill, fitting none but Soueraigne States and Kings, muſt ſtint the values, and guide the proportions of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> in all Materialls beſides. But all <hi>Goodnes</hi> is needfull. <hi>Exchange</hi> therefore, as the Spirit in the Soule, to perfect our <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by the Fountaines of<note n="1" place="margin">Staples.</note> 
                  <hi>Bullion,</hi> and ſtore of Princes<note n="2" place="margin">Mynts.</note> 
                  <hi>Coyne,</hi> in reſpect of the vſe there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, ought to be generall. Foraſmuch as the <hi>good</hi> intended there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, is ſo due to all, as cannot be diſturbed or reſtrained to anie, without diſorder and confuſion, for <hi>Omne Bonum, eſt ſui diffuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This I ſay then, is that treble-twiſted thred, twyned by louing and loyall <hi>Ariadne,</hi> to guide our fatall THESEVS by, thorowe all the Muces and Mazes of that <hi>Labyrinth</hi> of Errors, <hi>(Marchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dizing Exchange,)</hi> to free and redeeme the Bodies of Men, and Soules of Chriſtians, from the yeerely, monthly, and daily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouring Iawes of that Monſter of <hi>Creete,</hi> and Bawde of <hi>Bankers, (Vſury,)</hi> to the rayſing againe, and perfect vniting of <hi>Religion</hi> &amp; <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> that Mercy and Truth among Men, may ſit kindly toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and Righteouſnes and Peace may kiſſe each other.</p>
               <p>Thus all things in Nature doe tend to perfection by the Rules of <hi>Order,</hi> and degrees of <hi>Goodnes:</hi> but the vſe makes all. For <hi>Quò mihi Fortuna ſi non conceditur vti?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The vſe of <hi>Mettalls,</hi> both Gold and Siluer, as cheefeſt materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls for Princes <hi>Coyne,</hi> is in this reſpect ſo vrgently needfull, that where <hi>Nature</hi> fayles, <hi>Art</hi> muſt make good: in which regard, the want of Mynes in this Kingdome, hath beene euer ſupplyed by forraine <hi>Bullion,</hi> and auncient <hi>Customes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The want of <hi>Coyne</hi> in the Princes Treaſurie, ſhewes defect of <hi>Naturall Mynes,</hi> or neglect of artificiall Supplyes, whereof <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> is chiefeſt. Neither is it enough, fit, nor conuenient, that bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing prouided, or brought to the Mynt,<note place="margin">Cudendae monetae Ius proprium eſt Principis et inde publicae fiunt.</note> (the publicke pulſe and hart of <hi>Trafficke,</hi>) priuate Subiects preſume to coyne it for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: leaſt thereby Kings become ſeruaunts to their owne Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalls, and conſtrained to borrow that ſhould be apt to lend. A courſe in Nature both miſerable and prepoſterous. For what har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der condition, then to ſee <hi>Clothiers</hi> compeld to worke out other mens <hi>Wooll,</hi> for a ſhred in the end of the ſelfe-ſame cloth? Yet this is worſe. For where all Trades are valued by, and vented for Money, this makes Coyne both diſvalue &amp; ſell it ſelfe. <hi>O hyſteron
<pb facs="tcp:15002:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>proteron,</hi> &amp; ground of all Diſorder. If KINGS aboue themſelues haue none but GOD, that only makes <hi>homage</hi> ioyne <hi>honor</hi> to their Crownes, and ſeeing their ſeruice doth yeelde them reward, all others below them beeing proſtrate at their feete, the names of Wages and Fees, is too baſe for Soueraignes from beneath them to receiue: and for Subiects to offer, prepoſterous, perſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and euery way prophane.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtantinus Magnus,</hi> ne aliter quam ſanctè et legitimè hoc regale vterctur: effigiem ſuam nummu ſic inſeulpi voluit, vt hominis Deu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> flexis genibus invocantis prae ſe ferret. Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neta aute<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dicta quod moneat ne quid frandis in Materia ſigno vel pondere fiat.</note>If then the Type of Princes be their Thrones and Dignitie; if the Obiect of their Actions, (next the glory of that <hi>Deitie</hi> whom they repreſent,) be their owne greatnes &amp; honour; if Marchants buy and ſell <hi>Goodnes</hi> but for theyr owne auaile; what greater gaine then for Subiects to attaine to their Soueraignes <hi>Dignitie?</hi> And what harder eſtate, then to ſee Kings ſet a worke, and waged by their Seruants?</p>
               <p>If the Law pronounce it death, (and that moſt worthilie) to counterfet Princes Coynes, by what meanes ſoeuer; vvhat can expiat that ſinne of Preſumption, that as it were with their owne Hands and Stampes, vſurpe their <hi>Preheminence,</hi> and diſturbe their <hi>Exchange?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In a word, let the hart by the lyuer, receiue his tinctured <hi>Chy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> by his owne mouth and ſtomacke, and the blood with the Spirits ſhall fill all the vaines. And if Nature haue taught all men to affect the generall <hi>Good</hi> by particular Trades, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted each Trade his proper Materialls by the helpe and vſe of Money, leaue <hi>Bullion</hi> for Princes, and the World can vvant no Coyne; the eaſie courſe and recourſe of whoſe <hi>Exchange,</hi> ſhall ſet all things in tune, and ſerue all Mens turnes.</p>
               <p>But to compare things by contraries, will beſt illuſtrate either. Wee all cry out of <hi>Couetyſe</hi> and <hi>Priuate-gaine,</hi> as good reaſon, for GOD himſelfe hath pronounced it the roote of all Euill, and the loue of Money to be flat Idolatry. Which being bad in <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,</hi> muſt needes be worſt in <hi>Kings:</hi> How great then muſt our happines appeare, to haue <hi>Bounty</hi> it ſelfe come dwell among vs? And what hartie remorſe ought it to moue to ſome him and his, abridged or depriued of the principall meanes to practiſe theyr vertues?</p>
               <p>Great therefore, greater, and greateſt of all, muſt theyr Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts be to GOD and <hi>Nature,</hi> that prepoſterouſly peruerting his proper Materialls, turne his beſt helps for <hi>Bullion</hi> to their pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uate aduantage? to the intollerable diſturbance both of Court &amp; Country, and almoſt vnrecouerable wrong to the King and his Crowne. Wherein <hi>Customers</hi> wanting wordes to ſet out theyr griefes, haue made ſignes with their<note n="*" place="margin">The ſecond Reply. or Treatiſe of <hi>Exchange. &amp;c.</hi>
                  </note> pennes. And yet ceaſe not by Prayer to groane in this manner.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <l>O that our Tongues or Pennes could but expreſſe,</l>
                  <l>Or had the giſt to make Men vnderſtand</l>
                  <l>Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> great Effects of ſacred happines</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Exchange</hi> (alone) would worke, by <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Counſells</hi> hand:</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Religious Iuſtice</hi> ſhould then ſo bleſſe our Land,</l>
                  <l>That Men on Earth might ſee by this <hi>Idea</hi> made,</l>
                  <l>What Heauen it ſelfe doth boade in this our Kingly Trade.</l>
               </q>
               <p>So farre off, are <hi>Customers</hi> from guilt in this behalfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Now ſee but what is paſt, &amp; ſo put all together, to heare what words they ſpell.</p>
               <p>That,<hi>Goodnes</hi> (whoſe Standerd is DEITIE,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Kaloca' gathia,</hi> id eſt, <hi>Aequum et Bonum, Honeſtum et V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile:</hi> Beauty and Bountie, Profit &amp; Pleaſure.</note>) applyed to the actiue perfections of <hi>Commutaliue Right,</hi> by the rules of our Booke, and ſcope of our Leſſon, is a beautifull aſpect, and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiall influence of Heauenly Beatitude, in the operations of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Art, (which in Greeke is vnderſtoode by <hi>Calocagathia.</hi>) Sanctifying and aſſuring the formall Eſſence of all happy Beings:<note place="margin">And GOD ſawe that all hee had made was exceeding <hi>Good.</hi>
                  </note> For <hi>Bono ſuo consta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Omnia.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Bullion</hi> or <hi>Billion,</hi> is a worde of Art, giuen to the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall perfections of purenes and finenes in the ſolide Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities of Gold and Siluer,<note place="margin">Deprehenſum a peritioribus eſt, in Mundi creatione, principe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Deum Arithmetica eſſe vſum, Geometria <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Muſica, ſiquide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Arithmetica ratio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>pacta connexaqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> creduntur Elementa: Geometria vero Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guras effinxit vt inde ſirmitatem conſe que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renter, ſtabilitatem ac pro Naturae vi mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitatem. Proportiones adnexuit Muſicane terra plus in terreno ſentiretur Elemento, quam Aquae in Aqueo, et in acreo aeris <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t Ignu in ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>a Natura: nec Elementorum vllum omnino, in aliud reſolui vlla ratione quires. Proinde, quum audis a <hi>DEO</hi> eſſe vniuerſa in numero creata et pondere ac menſura: intellige ad Arithmeticam Nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merum referri, pondus ad Muſicam ad Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ometraim vero Menſurae ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ectum Nomen. Quippe astringente grauitatem leuitate co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fouentur omniafulciu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur que: in meditullio namque, ign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> potestate cohibetur Terra, ſed et huic ignis innititur. Ita prof<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>cto est, Magnitudo Exquiſitiſsimi, nec laudati vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam pro dign<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tate Operis; necnon late pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tens vis et motus, admirabilem Opificu prae ſe fert potentiam. Diſpoſitio vero excul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsima, mirificam ost entat Sapientia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Vſiu vero ad optimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbi<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ducens latius exu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>birantem nobis ingerit bonitatem. Proinde ſummi Platonici vniuerſum hoc v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lut au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustiſsimam Dei ſtatuam eximie venerati ſunt. Et que in co caeteris Maiestate Naturae praestare videntur, tanquam Idearum cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiora Simulachra. <hi>Caelij Rodigini, Lib. 1. Cap. 2.</hi>
                  </note> layd out by nature at the Standert of TRVTH, to fixe the proportions of <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best</hi> in, for the eaſier extention of <hi>Goodnes,</hi> by vendible <hi>Commerce:</hi> For, as <hi>Omne Bonum est ſui diffuſiuum:</hi> ſo <hi>Quantò communius eò melius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That <hi>Money</hi> or <hi>Coyne,</hi> is a figured proportion of <hi>Number</hi> and <hi>Weight,</hi> layd out by Art at the Standerd of IVSTICE to weigh the <hi>degrees</hi> of <hi>Goodnes</hi> by, in all thinges vendible; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t quod vſpiam <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ſcitur Boni, id apud omnes affluat.</hi> The woorth whereof, none but Soueraine-wiſedome can iuſtly value or equalize, and abſolute Authoritie ſtampe and make currant: becauſe, <hi>Omne quod efficit Tale, id ipſum eſſe magis Tale oportet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And. That <hi>Exchange</hi> (whoſe Standerd is EQVITIE,) is that Rule is <hi>pollicie</hi> and gouernment of <hi>State,</hi> which ſencibly demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates thoſe heauenly Effects of <hi>Power</hi> &amp; <hi>Wiſedome</hi> that DEITIE imparts to mortall <hi>Gods,</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Counſailes</hi> on Earth, by meanes of Money, to maintaine the worth, and ſhewe the true vſe of all Thinges in <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by their proper Obiects, &amp; peculiar Ends.</p>
               <p>That as <hi>Goodnes</hi> Diuinely ſublimated, becomes onely fixt in <hi>Bullion:</hi> and <hi>Bullion</hi> onely coynd, deuides the proportions of <hi>Good, Better,</hi> and <hi>Best,</hi> reciuing life in it ſelfe from Soueraine Eſſence, becomes currant withall, through all the parts of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible <hi>Commerce:</hi> to ſhew the preheminent potencie that PRIN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES haue aboue their <hi>Subiects:</hi> So <hi>Exchange</hi> meaſuring propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in Gold and Siluer by weights of <hi>more</hi> or <hi>leſſe,</hi> to vphold the iuſt value, and maintaine the true vſe of <hi>Goodneſſe,</hi> as well of all things in <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by Coyne, as in Coyne it ſelfe; ſets forth their
<pb facs="tcp:15002:14"/>ſinguler <hi>Care, Prouidence, Prudence</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The orderly practiſe whereof being outwardly obſerued, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſts in the ready exchange of currant Coyne, purged and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>repa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by the fire of their Mynts, for dead or droſſie <hi>Bullion,</hi> layde downe at the Altars of their publick Temples, for<note n="*" place="margin">That is to ſay, Wares ſo cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red at the <hi>Staples</hi> before they come to the Ports to croſſe the Seas, as vpon the honour of the Kingdom, and credite of the Perſons &amp; Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces that firſt aſſoorde them, are made as vendible without all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibilitie of fraude or deceit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Seller to the Buyer, as are our <hi>Sandwich</hi> Bayes. &amp;c.</note> 
                  <hi>Stapled-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities,</hi> as the word it ſelfe both ſpells and imports. But the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie of this Art, is quietly conueyd in the lending and loanes of currant Coyne to ſuch as want, vpon equall termes of HOMAGE and TRVST. The End of <hi>Money</hi> being to make all things ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dible, by equalitie of worth, and value of it ſelfe, for the qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ker diſpatch and aduauncement of <hi>Trafficke:</hi> and the <hi>Ends</hi> of <hi>Trafficke</hi> the Soueraignes <hi>honour,</hi> the Kidgdomes <hi>peace,</hi> and the Subiects <hi>wealth.</hi> Thus mouing and diſpoſing all mens Endeuours, by wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Courſes, and perpetuall Motions, to ſerue and worke for ONE, and that ONE made able to maintaine the <hi>Syntheſis,</hi> and protect the freedome of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> by fitting all Mens turnes.</p>
               <p>And thus is <hi>Trafficke</hi> made the true and aſſured practiſe of that <hi>mysticall Phyloſophy,</hi> wherein ſo many wits haue ſpent the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues, &amp; blowne the coales in vaine;<note place="margin">¶ Lapis Phyloſophicus.</note> whoſe heaue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y <hi>Elixar, (Goodnes,)</hi> the Quinteſſence of <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Art,</hi> by Diuine ſublimation ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyde to Materialls, breedes Myſteries in Trades, and purging all droſſe of deceit from Trades, turnes Trades into Mettalls, and all Mettalls into pure Siluer, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> fine Gold.</p>
               <p>And <hi>Exchange</hi> becomes that <hi>Cordiall preſeruatiue,</hi> which eaſing all griefes and ſores,<note place="margin">¶ Vniuerſalis Medecina.</note> ſuppling all ſores in diſeaſes, and curing all diſeaſes in particular Members, holds the whole Body of King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in health. The ſacred Rules whereof, as no prophane Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetyſe could euer comprehend, nor confident Empericke attaine to practiſe; ſo none of priuate Diſcretion, or partiall Affection, may preſume to alter or controll, as being a Doctrine peculiar to the <hi>Grauest</hi> and <hi>Wiſest</hi> in higheſt Authoritie, and for PRINCES themſelues.</p>
               <p>Of <hi>Trafficke</hi> then, by Nature ſo admirable, and by Art made ſo amiable, thus wonderfully wrought, &amp; orderly taught by Rules of TRVTH, IVSTICE &amp; EQVITY, what can be leſſe ſaid, then, that her Doctrine is Heauenly, and fit for none but <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Counſaile-Tables,</hi> her ſeate beeing euery-where the Soueraignes owne Boſome. Whoſe voyce well tunde, is the harmonie of the World; to whom both Courts and Courtiers owe <hi>Fealtie</hi> &amp; <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage:</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaneſt Subiects feeling her Care, and the greateſt Princes ſubiect to her Prouidence; whom both Noble and Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noble admire, and loue as the Nurſe and Protectreſſe of all their earthly <hi>Honours, Proſperities, Peace</hi> and <hi>Ioy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Since GOODNES then is that purging Fire, that ſent from Heauen, can onely purifie from droſſe of Deceit, all the Materi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alls prepared and preſented at the ſanctified Altars of publique
<pb facs="tcp:15002:14"/>Commerce, to make <hi>Kings</hi> adored, &amp; <hi>Subiects</hi> happy: And Gold and Siluer, of all ſolide <hi>Bodies,</hi> the apteſt and ſureſt for generall behoofe to fixe this <hi>Goodnes</hi> in: No maruaile at all, if all men,<note place="margin">Vt mundo Natura Curſum. Soli Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men et Aquae fluxum, ſic gratia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro.</note> if all men, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miring the <hi>Beautie</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> of the One and the Other, ſo ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly affect them as their chiefeſt Treaſure.</p>
               <p>But admit it were graunted, that ſome One Man alone might become poſſeſſed of all the Gold which the world doth co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>taine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f all the Siluer that Nature affoordes; or each Man as much as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is hart could wiſh, yet the ſame vncoynd, would prooue but idle or comberſome, for want of publicke vſe. For though <hi>Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> by DEITIE vniuerſally infuſed, and in <hi>Bullion</hi> fixed by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke conſent, be ſufficient for worth to ſet foorth it ſelfe, yet till <hi>Soueraigntie</hi> by Wiſedome appoynt out their vſe, &amp; Power make them Currant; euen <hi>Coyne</hi> is not Coyne, and hath no life at all, but reſts a weight of maſſy Mould, and ſenceleſſe <hi>Beeing.</hi> VVoe woorth then all thoſe PROMETHEY, that for priuate reſpects, ſteale this Heauenly-fire, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the holy<note n="1" place="margin">Mynts, by Coyning for them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues.</note> Altars of <hi>Vnity</hi> &amp; <hi>Truth,</hi> and in contempt of <hi>Maiestie,</hi> rob and engroſſe the publicke ſtore of our<note n="2" place="margin">Staples, by Monopolies.</note> 
                  <hi>Temples</hi> of <hi>Iustice.</hi> And all thoſe NADABS and ABI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HVES, that offering ſtrange fire, from prophane Altars of priuie<note n="3" place="margin">Counterfetters of Coyne.</note> 
                  <hi>Preſumption,</hi> ſeeke to poyſon our <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and all parts of <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Money</hi> in a Kingdome, beeing the ſame that Blood is in the <hi>Body,</hi> and all Allayes but humors. For when the Standerd of <hi>Goodnes</hi> in Gold and Siluer, is vnſteddily fixt, &amp; <hi>Money</hi> in weight vnconſtantly Coyne, &amp; for vſe vnwoorthily Currant, as all <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities</hi> beſides, become deerer and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>; that is to ſay, of more eſteeme then <hi>Money</hi> it ſelfe: So the People of that Kingdome, grow troubled, and vnquiet within themſelues, according to the baſenes of the Coyne when it is perceiued.</p>
               <p>That KING then that puts in his <hi>Coyne</hi> much <hi>Bullion,</hi> and little <hi>Allay,</hi> makes Himſelfe powerfully admyred, his Nobles reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuely honoured, and his Commons obediently diligent, and all Men willing to raiſe themſelues by their Induſtries and Trades; holding their times well ſpent, and labours well employed, for ſuch Money as they beleeue and find to be perfect Treaſure.</p>
               <p>Contrariwiſe, he that puts much <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>y</hi> to little <hi>Bullion,</hi> makes <hi>Maiestie</hi> it ſelfe, contemptibly weake; the <hi>Nobles,</hi> neglectedly deſpiſed; and the <hi>Commons,</hi> ſtubbornly careleſſe, to worke for that, they find afore-hand and know, not woorth their labour: The onely way to Reputation and Wealth, beeing left to <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Tillage</hi> and <hi>Honeſt Graſing. Victus</hi> &amp; <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>estitus</hi> being euerie Mans want. Neceſſity vpholding the eſtimation of their <hi>Commodities</hi> far aboue <hi>Baſe-Money,</hi> whilſt all men ſeeke to them, &amp; they almoſt to no man.</p>
               <p>And as a ſteddy Standerd, and ſtore of Coyne in the Princes
<pb facs="tcp:15002:15"/>Treaſury, makes all things els cheape, holds Trades in requeſt, ſhewes Kings to be powerfull, and Subiects wealthy: ſo, as the <hi>Standerd</hi> falls vncertaine, and Money engroſt into priuate handes, all things grow deere, the King becomes weake, and his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects poore, whilſt Coyne it ſelfe by <hi>Vſury</hi> in <hi>Marchandizing Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> eates out Induſtry and Trades;<note place="margin">Marchandizing Exchange.</note> and <hi>Marchandizing Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants</hi> by MONOPOLIES, conſpyre to ſtrangle <hi>Trafficke.</hi> Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples hereof may be <hi>Edw:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">MONOPOLYES.</note> 3. 1338. at his going to conquer <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> And <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. ouerwhelmed by warres at home.</p>
               <p>For <hi>Money</hi> is not regarded for the Name-ſake, but for weight of true worth, and vſe of currant value. King <hi>Henry</hi> the 3. in his pound, or xx. s. of currant Siluer coyne, put xij. ounces ſterling. Which then was, and yet is worth an ounce of fine Gold, and ſo was payd his Rent. <hi>Edw:</hi> 4. rayſd that ounce to fortie ſhillings, which hee found but at foure Nobles. And <hi>Edw:</hi> 6. receiued no more in eyght pounds-rent of Siluer coyne, then xij. ounces ſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling; and ſo loſt to himſelfe &amp; his Nobility ſeauen parts of their Reuenewes, the Land beeing the ſame it was in <hi>Hen:</hi> 3. time, &amp; not rayſed in proportion; which theyr Tenants euer found.</p>
               <p>The way to retayne <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> within a Kingdome, and draw more vnto it, is to hold a perfect and ſteddy Standerd at home, &amp; call all Forraine-coynes currant, one penny in an ounce of Siluer, and xij. pence in Gold aboue their owne. But aboue all that can be ſaid, or any way deuiſed, maintaine the Spring-head, <hi>(Trafficke,)</hi> and when all wants are ſupplyed,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trafficke,</hi> a more aſsured meanes to ſupply our King with <hi>Bullion,</hi> then the Mynes of INDIA.</note> the waſt will ſeeme needfull, or at leaſt not much regarded.</p>
               <p>And thus is Gold and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>luer (the ſeates of <hi>fixed Goodnes,</hi>) fitlie <hi>ab effectis,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Auro et Argento, Quid non?</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing GOD and a good cauſe to friend.</note> called <hi>King</hi> &amp; <hi>Queene</hi> of the world, in making Kings as powerfull in their Thrones, to protect their Subiects both by Sea and Land, &amp; diſpoſe of <hi>Trafficke</hi> within their Kingdoms, as GOD by <hi>Goodnes,</hi> in <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> &amp; <hi>Meaſure,</hi> firſt made the world, and ſtill doth guide the ſame. Each KING beeing an <hi>Idea</hi> of DEITIE it ſelfe, ſo much excelling in <hi>Preheminence</hi> of power for his <hi>Perſon</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> and in <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> of wiſedome for <hi>Affection</hi> and <hi>Loue,</hi> by how much they endeuour, to expreſſe in themſelues, and extend vnto others, the Characters of their <hi>Maiestie,</hi> &amp; Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles of their <hi>Glory,</hi> (IVSTICE and MERCY,) in the true vſe of <hi>Coyne.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe <hi>Mathematicks</hi> are <hi>Acroamaticall,</hi> fit for ALEXAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DER the great, and ARISTOTLE the wiſe, to walke &amp; diſcourſe of, <hi>Horis matutinis in Gymnaſio Lyceo,</hi> by themſelues all alone, and not for vs to ſpeake of, or ſpell. Neither had we thus preſumed (deſpiſed as we are) from our deſolate <hi>Schooles,</hi> and lowly <hi>Cotta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> to ſteppe into the Court, and enter the Mazes of theſe ſacred grounds,<note place="margin">The onely cauſe of publiſhing heereof in this ſort.</note> but to beate downe and preuent the dangerous <hi>Sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions</hi> of Imaginary Doctrine, and <hi>Legete de maine</hi> wherwith ſome
<pb facs="tcp:15002:15"/>Speculatiue Men, riſen vp in our time, bewitch all they meete, and (were it but poſſible,) would ſeduce the Wiſe: who ſeuering themſelues from the <hi>Body</hi> of our Commerce, and wandering out of fight, to keepe all men ſtill vnder, &amp; themſelues aboue, would perſwade the world, that <hi>Trafficke</hi> of herſelfe is a perillous byting beaſt; and that to bring her home to her owne Creekes &amp; Ports, muſt needes deſtroy all our Sheepe in <hi>Cotſall,</hi> and decay all our Shypping on <hi>Cheuiat-hills,</hi> and <hi>Barham-downes:</hi> which Aſſertion of theirs, ſo ſtrangely vndertaken, and ſtifly maintained, if ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fond nor falſe, yet is it but as true, as the building and raiſing of <hi>Tenterden-ſteeple,</hi> was the ruine and decay of our <hi>Sandwich-Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen,</hi> whom Land and Seas haue ſet ſome 30. miles aſunder. For confutation whereof, this place and time requires that ſomthing now be ſaid to ſatisfie the Wiſe, though I muſt confeſſe the eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes is ſuch, that how to diſpute it in any ſerious manner, I cannot well deuiſe.</p>
               <p>¶ All Aſſertions whatſoeuer, that fall within the compaſſe of humaine Diſcourſe, are made and maintained eyther by pregnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of Wit, cleerenes of Reaſon, or demonſtratiue Experience, (for againſt Diuine Reuelations wee meane not to diſpute,) the Minde conſulting ſtill with memory, and fancies Conceits. In which reſpect it is, that <hi>Imagination</hi> is truly termed the Store<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe of Wit, Memories Seate, and Fancies Pallace. By meanes whereof, as the pulſe declares beſt how the hart doth worke; ſo the thoughts of our Mindes, to purpoſe good or bad, doe ſoonſt bewr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y themſelues.</p>
               <p>Vppon this Anuile then we will begin to ſtrike, and entering this Cloſet, demaund of theſe aſſured and confident Diſputers, ſo boldly conteſting againſt all Commers, that the bringing home of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> muſt needes decay our Shipping; whether their wits in ſo deeming, be within them or without them. If they aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, Within them, as likely they will: then they, (without their wits,) muſt needes be diſtracted, franticke, or mad. And who is able <hi>cum ratione inſanire?</hi> And if to mend themſelues, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe theyr wits to be without them, then muſt they ſtand as wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, their Conceits beeing but Dreames, and their Dreames but Fancies.</p>
               <p>But let their wits alone, and leaue them to their fancies, till they finde one the other, for perhaps they ſee more reaſon then their Wits can deuiſe, or Conceits can vtter; I aske them then, (as men that would ſeeme at leaſt to vnderſtand the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues;) whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by this (our <hi>Shipping,</hi>) they meane Ships of <hi>Burden,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">All Shyps are cyther for Burden, or Defence.</note> or Ships of <hi>Defence,</hi> or both, or neither?</p>
               <p>If they ſay Shyps of <hi>Burden.</hi> How ſhould fancy or frenſie, by Diſcourſe of Wit or Reaſon, maintaine a Conceit, and perſwade it vnto others, which Experience in the Ports doth dailie con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne,
<pb facs="tcp:15002:16"/>and demonſtratly controll? Complayning ſtill for want of Keyes, Docks, and Wharfes to build on. Not of <hi>Matter,</hi> but of <hi>Place,</hi> where <hi>Trafficke</hi> once doth come, and but vnmaske her face.</p>
               <p>And ſhould we thinke it poſſible, that ſhe which hath had the power to turne <hi>Creekes</hi> into <hi>Ports,</hi> adde <hi>Ports</hi> vnto <hi>Townes,</hi> rayſe <hi>Townes</hi> into <hi>Citties,</hi> and enrich whole <hi>Countries</hi> with <hi>Artificers</hi> &amp; <hi>Trades, Marriners</hi> and <hi>Shipping,</hi> with our Neighbours abroad in leſſe then 50. yeeres, ſhould proue ſo idle, nay hurtfull now at home?<note place="margin">Ships carry <hi>Trafficke,</hi> as wheeles doe the Chariot. And <hi>Traffick</hi> the trimphant Coach that beares the Glory of our KING the Worlde round about.</note> 
                  <hi>Trafficke</hi> is the Chariot, &amp; <hi>Shypping</hi> are the Wheeles that beare our glorious LIGHT, and is that <hi>Body</hi> ſhadowleſſe that neuer wants the SVNNE?</p>
               <p>But ſtill they ſeeme to mutter much, and muſe among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, framing Concluſions without the bounds of Reaſon, or due regard of all our former premiſſes, to ſee if feare with fancie may perſwade the Wiſe. That if <hi>Trafficke</hi> be reſtored, and Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers compeld to ſeeke her heere at home; it is not vnlikely, but to ſexue their Turnes, they will come prouided with Shypping of their owne. And then what? Forſooth, though <hi>Trafficke</hi> make vs rich (as no queſtion but ſhee will,) what bootes our Wealth, when <hi>Innaſion</hi> or <hi>Pyracie</hi> may rob vs of our ſtore?</p>
               <p>To which I aunſwere thus. Let Saylers tend their Tacklings, their Maiſters whiſtle, and Captaines high commaund: Bring home our <hi>Staples,</hi> and CASTOR and POLLVX the GODS of our Seas, made able and powerfull to warrant our <hi>Trafficke,</hi> skilfull PALINVRVS that ſits at our Helme, obſeruing our Compaſſe, will ſafely guide our <hi>Courſe,</hi> and direct all our <hi>Shypping. Protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> and <hi>Direction</hi> beeing eſſentiall parts of that <hi>Preheminent, Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Nany-Royall before <hi>Sluſe,</hi> 1340. And before <hi>Callais,</hi> 1588.</note> and ſacred <hi>Prerogatiue</hi> our KINGS haue euer had, <hi>Experience</hi> hath confirmed, and our <hi>Counſells</hi> may challenge.</p>
               <p>This care and feare therefore comes too neere our Sterne, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porting a diſtruſt of the prouidence and prudence of our Land, and ſauors of Preſumption,<note place="margin">Blaſphemie.</note> or ſome-thing worſe.</p>
               <p>Theſe curious caſters beyond the Moone, would goe further if they durſt, and enquire how GOD can hold the Sky, &amp; keepe the Sunne from falling; Or what hee did before the World vvas made.</p>
               <p>But admit it that affection and loue to <hi>Trafficke, (ne quid aſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,)</hi> haue made them fearefull of others good, and icalous of their owne; I wiſh the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to beware how they come too neere the <hi>Helme</hi> for touching the <hi>Rudder.</hi> For what got PROMETHEVS for his Sky-ſtolne fire at laſt, from the wheeles of this Chariot, when the ſimple <hi>Satyre</hi> for kiſſing it in kindneſſe onely, found it burnt his lyppes?</p>
               <p>Leauing therefore all thoſe <hi>Holy</hi> grounds, and <hi>Cordialls</hi> of GOODNES to our ſacred IDEAS of <hi>Maiestie</hi> and <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> that
<pb facs="tcp:15002:16"/>beeing <hi>Best</hi> themſelues, muſt needes be <hi>Good</hi> to others, but ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially <hi>Trafficke,</hi> whoſe heauy Spirits, ſo tumbled &amp; ſo toſt by <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bargoes</hi> abroade, and <hi>Extremities</hi> at home, deſirous of ſome reſt; repoſing her ſelfe at their ſanctified feete, giues vs likewiſe leaue to returne to our Bookes, and ſpell out our Leſſon.</p>
               <p>Now our Leſſons are her <hi>Tributes</hi> and perſonall <hi>Rights,</hi> vvhich Neceſſity doth call for, and Free-will doth offer: namely, <hi>Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi> but chiefely <hi>Customes,</hi> which onely &amp; alone could we once be taught diſtinctly but to read, would eaſe all our <hi>Griefes,</hi> increaſe all our<note n="*" place="margin">This is meant by the OVT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PORTS onely.</note> 
                  <hi>Fees,</hi> and pay for all her Phiſicke. For <hi>Customes</hi> then, lets now apply our ſelues, and ſpell our Letters.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Customes</hi> (I ſay,) but not ſuch <hi>Customes</hi> as conquering <hi>Romans</hi> deuiſed, and impoſed vpon the ſtubburne and ſtifnecked <hi>Iewes,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">IVDEA.</note> whoſe Tributes were Curſſes of Diuine <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> to keepe them vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. Whoſe<note n="*" place="margin">S. MATTHEVV, ſometimes a <hi>Publican.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Publicans</hi> became <hi>Christians</hi> themſelues, and taught the foundations of <hi>Religion</hi> to others, though their <hi>Searchers</hi> by nature became <hi>Harpyes,</hi> and their <hi>Wayters</hi> by profeſſion, were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way <hi>Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nor ſuch <hi>Customes</hi> as <hi>Tyranny</hi> doth inuent,<note place="margin">ITALIE.</note> and daily impoſe vpon enthralled <hi>Subiects,</hi> to ſtand on, and raiſe it ſelfe by.</p>
               <p>Nor ſuch as tumultuous <hi>Warres</hi> haue made our Neigbours de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſe,<note place="margin">NETHER-LANDS.</note> and impoſe among and vpon themſelues, to defend theyr liues and their liberties by.</p>
               <p>But ſuch <hi>Customes,</hi> as mildnes and mercy to relieue our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, our Allies, and our Friendes, the Wiſedome of our Land hath inueſted our KINGS, to maintaine the <hi>Maieſtie</hi> of our Kingdome by.</p>
               <p>Such <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> as demonſtratiuely ſhewing the Reall poſſeſſion, &amp; Actuall protection, our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> hold of euery Mans welth, leaue notwithſtanding to euery Subiect his <hi>Meum</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> and full vſe of his owne.</p>
               <p>Laſtly, ſuch <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> as like eaſie <hi>Quit-rents</hi> of a fertile <hi>Fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>farme,</hi> ſhew the power of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and greatnes of the <hi>Manner,</hi> the defrauding whereof, doth worthily forfet all poſſeſſion and protection of the immediat <hi>Free-holder.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> of themſelues, and properly taken, are but eaſie payments of<note place="margin">a. e. i. o. u.</note> 
                  <hi>Currant-Money,</hi> to Cuſtomers at their <hi>Ports,</hi> by <hi>Marchants,</hi> Subiects or Strangers, for ſuch <hi>Stapled</hi> Commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as <hi>Orderly</hi> bought, and for Number, Weight, &amp; Meaſure, ſufficiently cenſured, before they croſſe the Seas; with the <hi>Staple</hi> Seale, and ſpeciall Certificate come warranted thether; for our Soueraignes <hi>Honor,</hi> and Countries credit.</p>
               <p>And heere now who ſees not in a very fewe wordes but thus put together, the full vſe and found of all our fiue Vowells, for <hi>Matter, Place, Perſons, Order,</hi> and <hi>End,</hi> that the <hi>Ports</hi> and the <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> ralate each to other.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:17"/>But as the <hi>Steward</hi> of a <hi>Mannor,</hi> that ſits to hold a Court, wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Rolls and autenticke Records of his Lords Reuenewes, can neither call the <hi>Tennants</hi> diſtinctly by their Names, demaund their <hi>Quit-rents,</hi> nor vnderſtand their Homage, how each doth bound his Fee, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hold his owne: ſo fares it with <hi>Customers.</hi> For beeing tyde to their Ports by carefull attendance, for diſcharge of their Bonds and peculiar truſt: Their wares without warrant, and their <hi>Staples</hi> out of ſight, from whence their worke ſhould come. Their Vowels all diſplaced, their Mutes are dombe, and Liquids iarre. For without <hi>u</hi> SIRS, and <hi>u</hi> my <hi>Lordes, <hi>w</hi>
                  </hi> hath no ſound,<note place="margin">u u w C. ſt. m. s.</note> to ſpeake or ſpell out <hi>Cuſtumes:</hi> and all for lacke of <hi>Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Staples!</hi> Now ſee ſee my Lords, for Gods ſake ſee, how <hi>Traffick</hi> falls a weeping,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trafficke,</hi> ſubiect to the <hi>Syncope,</hi> or great ſwounding which heere is deſcribed, and the remedies.</note> her pulſe is weake, &amp; her Spirits fayle, her face is pale and wan, at the name and ſound of <hi>Staples,</hi> the want wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſo wounds her Soule, that her hart is ſet on bleeding; yet co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort her ſtill, &amp; hold her vpright to keepe her from deadly ſwou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning: and ſpeake her fayre, that ſhe doe not deſpayre of the Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dialls in your onely keeping.</p>
               <p>Tell her kindly withall, <hi>Priuatio praeſupponit habitum,</hi> for neuer man yet was ſo continually ſicke, whoſe health hath not had a <hi>Beeing:</hi> and the diſproportioned diſpoſition of Confuſion it ſelfe, dooth argue an intention, and poſsibilite of Order. Therefore ſpeake my good Lords, to reuiue all her ſpirits, for your wordes are full of power; yea ſpeake aloude (I ſay) &amp; aſſure her you will belay all her <hi>Staples.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">KINGE PRINCE.</note> Yea, ſpeake you, and you (SIRS) for your <hi>Bullion</hi> ſake, for that is your right, and no mans but yours, by the Rules of all <hi>Truth,</hi> and fixed <hi>Goodnes.</hi> For your Mynts ſake, for that is your <hi>Honor,</hi> and no mans but yours by the Rules of <hi>Iuſtice.</hi> For your <hi>Exchange</hi> ſake, for that is your <hi>Glory,</hi> and no mans but yours by the Rules of <hi>Equality;</hi> and for your <hi>Customes</hi> ſake, for that is your profit, and no mans but yours, by the Rules of <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Equitie,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Quiquid enim Iuſtum, id etiam vtile cenſent ſumini Philoſophi, itemque quod honeſtu id eſſe Iuſtum. Ex quo eſſicitur. vt quicquid honeſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſit, idem ſit vtile. <hi>Cice: offic: lib: 2.</hi>
                  </note> ſo ſhall <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> concurre both together: <hi>Honeſtie</hi> beeing euermore the height and type of <hi>Honour,</hi> &amp; pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licke <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tilitie,</hi> the Mother of <hi>Iuſt</hi> and <hi>Right,</hi> for each mans good and gaine. Say not you can reſtore them, for that ſhee knowes already, but ſay you will doe it, and then ſhe will beleeue you. And wee your poore <hi>Schollers,</hi> loyall <hi>Subiects</hi> and <hi>Seruaunts,</hi> wil euery way attend you with all our beſt endeuours. Or els farwell ſweet <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and ſo farewell <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> yea farewell <hi>Iuſtice:</hi> nay farewell <hi>Religion,</hi> and then farewell <hi>All.</hi> So farre off are <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> from guilt alſo in this behalfe.</p>
               <p>But alas poore <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> who doth harken to your cryes, or beleeue your Reports? Who ſhall weigh your zeale, to our <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neraignes</hi> Honour, and his <hi>Peoples</hi> Good, or care for your Ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uors? Yet be not diſmaid; <hi>In magnis voluiſſe ſat eſt, ſint caetera Dinu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:17"/>Stand ſtill but awhile, and let GOD himſelfe alone. What though inveterate Errors of ages that are paſt haue multiplyed themſelues, and now ſeeme to muſter againſt our happy dayes: our DAYSTARRE that is riſen, and DAVVNING in our eyes,<note place="margin">KING. PRINCE.</note> will in good time diſperſe them, or amend them as they may, and take but thus much onwards. That <hi>Ignorance</hi> hath beene e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery way the Mother but of <hi>Errors,</hi> of whom came <hi>Miſchiefes,</hi> and of ſuch our <hi>Inconveniences,</hi> which though they threat <hi>Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> yet tell vs notwithſtanding, there is a way to <hi>Order,</hi> that leades vs to <hi>perfection,</hi> as <hi>Truth</hi> by the Cauſes of <hi>Truth</hi> ſhal come but to be knowne.</p>
               <p>Now <hi>Truth</hi> indeede lyes deepe, and the danger ſuch in dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that no man hath the patience to delue vntill they find her: &amp; I am to too weake (<note n="*" place="margin">The Wryter almoſt tyred &amp; out of hart, referres the <hi>Truth</hi> of all, to the Records of the K: <hi>Treaſury</hi> in his <hi>Exchequer,</hi> for Weights &amp; Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, <hi>Staple</hi> Accounts &amp; Orders.</note> alas,) to worke her out alone. O that WISDOME therfore which onely can diſcloſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, would make men admire thoſe glorious Titles of <hi>Iustice</hi> and <hi>Mercy,</hi> (Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blemes of <hi>Truth,</hi>) that the Volumes in her <hi>Cabinet,</hi> and <hi>Treaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> containes! Then ſhould wee learne the Rules and proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Numbers, Weights, and Meaſures. The vſe of <hi>Staples</hi> in former times, how they were kept, and whether they be gone. Then ſhould wee ſee thoſe wonderfull effects of our <hi>Loadſtones</hi> at home, that haue wrought ſuch miracles in other forraino Lands, and Nations from abroade, bringing <hi>Bullion</hi> in amaine, make our<note n="*" place="margin">Myntes.</note> 
                  <hi>Pulſes</hi> to beat in moe places the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> one. And we poore <hi>Schollers</hi> made confident in our <hi>Customes,</hi> without poſſibilitie of <hi>fraude,</hi> cauſe of <hi>distrust,</hi> or feare of <hi>blame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Cuſtomes in England, or in Engliſh <hi>Trafficke,</hi> alwayes preſuppoſe our <hi>Staples,</hi> and liue and dye or follow the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as Effects their proper Cauſes.</note>In the meane time, ſith no men can pipe well that want their vpper lyps, conſequence concludes it, and <hi>Truth</hi> makes it good, that as no <hi>Church</hi> hath no <hi>Tythes,</hi> and no <hi>Court</hi> no <hi>Quit-rents;</hi> ſo no <hi>Staples</hi> no <hi>Customes.</hi> Whereby <hi>Neceſſity</hi> ouertaken, beeing put to her ſhyfts, makes bold with <hi>Free-will,</hi> and to ayde PRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>HEMINENCE, tranſcending to PREROGATIVE,<note place="margin">The blending or miſtaking of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatine</hi> for <hi>Preheminence,</hi> a dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous meanes to prophane the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueraine effects and reuerence of Mercy in Kings.</note> turnes Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes into Subſidies of Tonnage and Pondage, as if PREHE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINENCE and PREROGATIVE were meerely <hi>Synonimas,</hi> and meant but one thing; and bounded <hi>Iuſtice</hi> that layes out all our Rights, were that boundleſſe <hi>Mercy</hi> that makes vs all to liue; and <hi>Mercy</hi> it ſelfe, but a word of prophanenes, or ſome ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie thing.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Marchants by Societies monopoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing our <hi>Staple</hi> Commodities, and Royall wares, haue found the way to Staple them ſtill beyond Seas, &amp; ſo confounding both our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> &amp; diverting all our <hi>Bullion,</hi> fill the Realme with baſer or more need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe matter in their returnes.</note>Thus whilſt our <hi>Graue Maiſters</hi> &amp; <hi>Moderators</hi> of our <hi>Schooles</hi> haue been buſied and diſtracted in the ſtudie and practiſe of the higher poynts of learning our <hi>Staples</hi> beeing ſtolne, tranſmuted and tranſplanted, our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> are confounded: and wee poore <hi>Schollers</hi> ſtill tyde to our <hi>Stakes,</hi> ſeeme fitte for nothing but bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and bayting. Hence grew the grounds of all our <hi>Diſorders,</hi> the breaches of our <hi>Schooles,</hi> and our<note n="*" place="margin">Trafficke.</note>
                  <hi>Nurſes</hi> deadly ſickneſſe, that threatned all our Ruines: had not <hi>Wiſedome</hi> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> aboue, out
<pb facs="tcp:15002:18"/>of <hi>loue</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> ſo belayde our falls, that the power of that WORD which made vs firſt of nothing, became the meanes to redeeme vs all from nothing; and<note n="*" place="margin">KING.</note> BOVNTIE it ſelfe hath laid the foundation, (and begun at the leaſt) to become the MAN: whereby our ioyes may be great,<note place="margin">The comfort that Cuſtomers co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue of the King and Prince.</note> and by ſo much the greater, by how much our greateſt loſſe (as all men thought) is like to become our greateſt gaine.</p>
               <p>Our comforts then growing from our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> owne PER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SON, and our hopes aboue hopes, from the power of his WORD; whoſe naturall ſtorge to <hi>Iuſtice</hi> and <hi>Right</hi> beeing euery vvay good, their <hi>affections</hi> alſo free, and <hi>loue</hi> without end: Lets heere reſt awhile, and ſetling our ſelues, both thinke and thanke <hi>God,</hi> and learne to ſay <hi>Grace,</hi> that <hi>Grace</hi> in diſgrace may pitty our caſes among the reſt, and raiſe our poore credites from im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent Ignorance, inſolent Pride, and ſhameleſſe Diſdaine: ſaying;</p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">The Cuſtomers daily Grace.</note>As <hi>God</hi> by his <hi>Goodnes</hi> and <hi>Truth</hi> did direct vs,</l>
                  <l>whoſe mercy endures for euer,</l>
                  <l>So his <hi>Grace</hi> and his <hi>fauour</hi> vouchſafe to protect vs,</l>
                  <l>for his mercy endures for euer.</l>
                  <l>That our <hi>Traffick</hi> by <hi>Staples</hi> in temper againe,</l>
                  <l>for his mercy endures for euer,</l>
                  <l>Our <hi>Ports</hi> with their <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> may chau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t it amaine</l>
                  <l>that his mercy endures for euer.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>Thus farre by poynting and ſpelling in this ALPHABET and PRIMER our weakenes hath attaynd to reſolue and read out. That the right of Kings beeing <hi>Bullion,</hi> their Honour theyr <hi>Coyne,</hi> theyr Glory their <hi>Exchange,</hi> and <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> their Homage and honeſt gayne: ſhewes that <hi>Maieſtie</hi> is preheminent and may well be ſeene, and that <hi>Soneraigne Prerogatine</hi> may likewiſe ſubſiſt. But our PATRONE being robd of his <hi>Staples,</hi> ſpoyld of his <hi>Bullion,</hi> and wanting the <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> ſhould growe from his ſtore; his <hi>Mynts</hi> all decayed, &amp; almoſt out of worke, is forſt to ſeeke ayde by <hi>Subſidies, Impoſitions, Impoſts, Lones</hi> of his owne for intereſt, and Marchants <hi>Supplyes.</hi> Aye mee alas, and woe is me therefore.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tranſitio</hi> from Cuſtomes to Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidies by a <hi>Simile,</hi> ſetting forth the oddes and difference of eyther.</note>There's a <hi>Place</hi> in this Land where a great Man doth dwell, in whoſe beautifull Garden a ſtately <hi>Fountaine</hi> ſtands, in the vſe and rayſing whereof, it ſeemes that Art contends with Nature, and both conſpire together. The <hi>Spring</hi> by plentifull <hi>ſtreames,</hi> through Pypes and Quills ſeruing all the <hi>Ceſternes</hi> of the <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants</hi> adioyning, with a power in priuate, to ſtoppe or let out at pleaſure. By tract of time, corruptions abroade, or neglect at
<pb facs="tcp:15002:18"/>home the <hi>Spring</hi> becomes perverted, the <hi>ſtreames</hi> runne waſt, or the <hi>Fountaine's</hi> out of frame, that the Lord of the ſoyle, vvho ſhould releeue others, by the bountie of his owne, wanting wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter himſelfe, craues ayde of the <hi>Tenants,</hi> whoſe <hi>Ceſternes</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine no more of themſelues then his currant afforded &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct controld. His wants at the firſt are gladly ſupplyed. But the ofter the worſe; for in theſe Elements of life and vitall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtence, <hi>Religion</hi> bids <hi>Reaſon</hi> prouide firſt for <hi>Nature,</hi> &amp; be next herſelfe. Diſtreſſes beeing dangerous, if not deadly, when the blood is retracted, and the <hi>Hart</hi> wants his owne.</p>
               <p>This muſt helpe for a time (till our <hi>Staples</hi> be found) by <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> and <hi>Tuum,</hi> betweene <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> and <hi>Subſidies,</hi>) to compare and demonſtrate, for want of the One, the vſe of the other.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">As in the two ſacred words of high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt power, aforeſaid: ſo in the blen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding &amp; miſtaking of <hi>Customes</hi> for <hi>Subſidies,</hi> Traffick is diſordered, &amp; Cuſtomers being diſgraced, hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bly craue that the worlde might be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, and the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues better taught.</note>But heere lets pauſe awhile, the better to ioyne our Letters together, and miſtruſting our ſelues, craue ayde of our <hi>Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> and <hi>Myld-Moderators:</hi> that hauing eyes which can ſee, they may helpe vs to ſpell, and eares that can heare, they may har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken how we reade, &amp; make vs vnderſtand. 1. Firſt, how it comes to paſſe, that our <hi>Staples</hi> beeing diſſolued or tranſplanted out of ſight (from whence all our <hi>Homagers</hi> were ſometimes vvont to come) and our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> retaining the leaſt part of themſelues, beſides their voyce &amp; ſound;<note place="margin">All Tributes couered vnder the ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle of Cuſtomes confuſedly.</note> all Tytles notwithſtanding ſeeme dyde with their Tincture, and drownd as it were, with the <hi>Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho</hi> of their Name. 2. And in calling for our <hi>Subſidies,</hi> where &amp; how to find out the <hi>Principall verbe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">The way how to collect Cuſtome confidently and truly.</note>For whilſt our <hi>Staples</hi> were at home, &amp; ioyned to our <hi>Ports,</hi> or ſo neere together, that each might anſwere other, our <hi>Loade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones</hi> drew in <hi>Bullion,</hi> for our <hi>Mynts</hi> at hand to coyne: and wee reading in our<note n="*" place="margin">The Staple-Certificats &amp; Cuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers-Entries, were certaine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolements each to other, without Bookes of Rates. The way to receiue Subſidies by Bookes of Rates, different fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that of Cuſtomes, and more partiall and vncertaine.</note> 
                  <hi>Rentalls</hi> as well in <hi>value</hi> as in <hi>quality</hi> &amp; <hi>quantitie,</hi> what our <hi>Marchants</hi> there had bought, could call iuſtly for our Cuſtomes before they croſt the Seas, without fraude or covyn, or other Booke of Rates. But in our <hi>Pondage</hi> and <hi>Tonnage,</hi> we know not how to reade or ſpell, and therefore ſeeke to learne. For,</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Haud Natura poteſt Iuſto ſecernere ìniquum,</l>
                  <l>
                     <note place="margin">Horatius.</note>Dividit vt bona diuerſis, fugienda petendis:</l>
                  <l>Nec vincet ratio hoc tantundem vt peccet. Idem<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan>,</l>
                  <l>Qui teneros Caules alieni fregerit horti</l>
                  <l>Et qui nocturans Diuum ſacra legerit. (<hi>ADSIT</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>REGVLA</hi>) peccatis qua poenas irroget aequas,</l>
                  <l>Ne ſcutica dignum horribili ſectere flagell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
               </q>
               <q>
                  <l>It is not our weake ſtrength alone can ſtay</l>
                  <l>Or hold the Skales of <hi>Good</hi> &amp; <hi>Ill</hi> vpright:</l>
                  <l>Nor is that <hi>Reaſon</hi> good that makes all one by day,</l>
                  <l>To crop a Neighbors garden-<hi>leekes,</hi> &amp; rob a Church by night:</l>
                  <l>
                     <pb facs="tcp:15002:19"/>A RVLE muſt guide the whole to keep the parts from ſwaruing,</l>
                  <l>And puniſh faults in euery one according to deſeruing.</l>
                  <l>And not to thinke that euery ſlippe,</l>
                  <l>Like deadly-Sinne deſerues a whippe.</l>
               </q>
               <p>For: If <hi>Soueraigne Dignitie</hi> be that ſacred <hi>Obiect</hi> which <hi>true<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louing Loyaltie</hi> is apt to admire, and ſeekes to honour with <hi>natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſpects,</hi> (ſuch as all <hi>Subſidies</hi> are or ought to be) who can be capable of ſo great a glory, by perſonall Right, but <hi>ſelfe-ſubſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Maiestie?</hi> and who can accept of ſo great affection, but the eye of <hi>Grace?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If theſe our <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> be thoſe <hi>naturall reſpects</hi> which loue is deſirous that loyaltie ſhould offer, to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour our <hi>Soueraigne</hi> and <hi>Patrone</hi> onely by, befides his Cuſtoms, who can impoſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> but Loues owne <hi>affection?</hi> who can eſteeme them but the hand of <hi>Mercy?</hi> and what can encreaſe them but <hi>cheerefull alacritie</hi> in the Giuers mind?</p>
               <p>Laſtly. If <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage</hi> be thoſe <hi>honourable Effectes</hi> of affectionate Loyaltie which Marchants tranſcending their o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther duties, with <hi>ioy</hi> preſent and <hi>Mercy</hi> takes. Who ſhall direct and dilate their proportions by <hi>Number, Weight,</hi> &amp; <hi>Meaſure,</hi> for the mutuall behoofe of <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Grace?</hi> VVho I ſay, can teach vs this part of our Leſſon, but the graueſt and Wiſeſt, and wiſedome from the Higheſt? namely, <hi>howe to deale Iuſtlie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene the Prince and the People?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For <hi>cheerefulneſſe</hi> and <hi>alacritie,</hi> inducements vnto <hi>Grace,</hi> the hart &amp; Eſſence of all our <hi>Aydes,</hi> (as coldneſſe in affection makes preſents little worth) whilſt we ſought to further, and by often repetition at all hands to encreaſe to our <hi>Patrons</hi> honor and his Peoples good,<note place="margin">Hoc autem de quo nunc agimus, id ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſum eſt quod vtile appellatur, in quo verbo lapſa co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſuetudo deflexit devia. Eo<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſenſam deducta eſt, vt honesta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem ab vtilite ſecernens honeſtum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquid conſtituerit quod non ſit vtile, et vtile quod non ſit honeſtum qua, nulla pernicies maior vitae hominu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuit afferri. <hi>Cicero offic: Lib: 2.</hi>
                  </note> that <hi>Honestum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> might ſtill keepe toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, by the rules of <hi>Right</hi> and <hi>Reaſon:</hi> Wee are checkt and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouled by <hi>Court-rolles</hi> and <hi>Court-rules,</hi> and made to beleeue that <hi>Honestie</hi> in this caſe hath naught to doe with <hi>Profit.</hi> Diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion commaunding the moſt for the King; as if <hi>Honour</hi> heere were booteleſſe, or ſome idle thing: and that <hi>publique Vtilitie</hi> were meant by <hi>priuate Gaine.</hi> We conteſt in nothing, but euerie way willing and deſirous for to learne, our <hi>harmeleſſe diſpoſitions</hi> are ſcornd and deſpiſed;<note place="margin">The mylde diſcretion of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> to aduaunce <hi>Subſidies</hi> by, deſpiſed.</note> our <hi>Truth</hi> is held for <hi>Errour,</hi> our <hi>Vertue <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ice.</hi> And for crying but ADSIT REGVLA, wee are dingd ſo like Barnes that we dare not greit. And thus with the grounds of our former Diſorders, began the degrees of all our Diſgra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; which the ſequell now ſhall ſhewe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>¶ As in all other Functions, ſo in this of <hi>Cuſtomers,</hi> three things there are to warrant the Calling, but without the fourth none can ſubſiſt. For beſide, the authoritie of our firſt Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb facs="tcp:15002:19"/>that giues vs power to be dooing in this kind. The Ports and Places allotted for Boundes that lymit our ſeruice. And the diligent performance which in this reſpect the greatnes of our truſt doth exact and import: There is Countenaunce &amp; main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenaunce to be fitted to our Charge, which in this regarde we deſerue &amp; may require. For the Oxe is not muzeled that trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth out the Corne. <hi>Religion</hi> ſayes. And <hi>Iustice</hi> hath appointed, that the daily Labourer be truly payd his hyre. But <hi>Nos non no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis indificamus Aues.</hi> We ſerue at the Altar both daily &amp; houre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and yet are held vnworthy to breathe or liue thereby. For beſides the penurie of ſuch Fees and Rewards as our Functions deſerue, and our charges require; our fare beeing ſlender, and our drinke very skant; we dip but our diſhes in our Neighbors <hi>Cesternes</hi> to quench our thirſt, and at Noone in his garden crop a few of his <hi>Leekes,</hi> with his owne conſent, to keepe vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving: And this addes oyle to the fire of our Furnace; heere lies the gall of all our bitterneſſe: Our breathes are ſaide to infect with their ſent, and poyſon the ayre.</p>
               <p>This is our horrrrible Sinne, our Sacriledge, or Burglarie at leaſt. As if <hi>We</hi> heereby, &amp; none but <hi>Wee,</hi> had ſpoyld the <hi>Kings Staples,</hi> ſtolne away his <hi>Bullion,</hi> conceald his <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> and at Midnight robd a Church. Of all this <hi>Ignorance</hi> but accuſing, our <hi>Huiſhers</hi> bynde vs hand and foote, and <hi>Iealoufie</hi> torments vs with a kinde of <hi>Controller.</hi> Whoſe skill can no wayes helpe vs, for his Letters are thoſe Characters that wee would ſpell to read; and <hi>Actum agere,</hi> the ſcope of all his Leſſon.</p>
               <p>This <hi>Man</hi> at the firſt ſeemes doubly diligent, till <hi>Experience</hi> makes him wiſe, beeing proude of his Name,<note place="margin">CONTROLERS.</note> and content with the eaſe of his Place and credite; but his belly wanting eares, he betakes him boldly to a Bed of <hi>Onyons,</hi> and ſpares our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours <hi>Leekes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now <hi>Leekes</hi> and <hi>Onyons</hi> thus meeting together,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>All mens errors and faults, ſtill layd on the</hi> Cuſtomers. Quonſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> tande<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> andebunt dicere, quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam vtile quod non ſit honeſtu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>? nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam enim peste<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> maiorem dixerim vita et ſocietati hominum poſſe contingere quam corum opinio qui ista diſtraxe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rint. <hi>Offic: Lib: 3.</hi>
                  </note> and increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the ſmel to our further diſgrace, and onely blame, made an eaſie way to our late <hi>Superviſors,</hi> and theyr <hi>Factions Retinewe.</hi> Whoſe rules of <hi>Extremity</hi> in hunting for Profit, and reforming our Schooles diſorder and Abuſes, ſo perfumed our <hi>Ports</hi> by ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Garlicke,</hi> that <hi>Honor</hi> and <hi>Honeſtie</hi> became both amazed, and remooud theyr Seates.</p>
               <p>Theſe at the firſt made a glorious ſhewe like the Moone at full, yet proou'd but <hi>Commets,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The 4. <hi>Superviſors</hi> that vndertake to correct Magnificat in the <hi>Out-Ports.</hi>
                  </note> for men to gaze on as they hung in the Ayre, and their greateſt Letters but <hi>Cyphers</hi> in Auguſt when they came to the ſpelling. For ſtuffing our <hi>Houſes</hi> vvith ſwarmes of ſuch Inſtruments as loue our Tributs but as Rats doe loue Cheeſe, ſo bewitchd poore <hi>Trafficke</hi> by Sorcerie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trafficke</hi> firſt bewitcht: And</note> and ſhyfts, that as our Ports became abandoned, like places in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected or haunted with Spirits: All our <hi>Free-will offerings,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The <hi>Out-Porti,</hi> firſt abandoned.</note> 
                  <hi>effectes</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:20"/>of <hi>Loyaltie;</hi> the true-<hi>loue-knots</hi> knit betweene <hi>Subiects</hi> &amp; <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>tokens</hi> of <hi>affection</hi> (religiouſly moou'd in mindes, admyring the glorious <hi>Obiect</hi> of their welfare and good) from the harts of Marchants: humbly preſented to Soueraigne <hi>Dignitie,</hi> and to man els due;<note place="margin">The Subſidies of <hi>Tonnage</hi> &amp; <hi>Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage</hi> farmed out.</note> 
                  <hi>Au plus offrant</hi> beeing ſet to ſale, were thruſt at laſt into Huxters handling. Theſe, ſome call <hi>particular Farmers,</hi> ſome <hi>Farmers generall,</hi> ſome <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers</hi> with <hi>Farmers,</hi> not ſo much of <hi>Cuſtomes,</hi> as they would pretend, as of the <hi>Subſidies</hi> afore ſaid, called <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>Qui male agunt oderunt Lucem.</q>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Farmers. Vndertakers.</note>The firſt ſort of theſe, may be ſeene and knowne. The latter, neither ſeene nor knowne in publique ſort, as <hi>Publicans</hi> be, haue yet their meetings and appointments together. And poſſeſſing the body, vndertake by meanes to purge the blood, and purifie the Spirits of our weake, diſeaſed and diſtracted <hi>Trafficke:</hi> ſome by <hi>Tabacco,</hi> and ſome by a <hi>worſe</hi> and <hi>viler</hi> thing. <hi>Cuìus Camari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam,</hi> I dare not ſtirre without pardon and reuerence, firſt hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly ſought, and duly promiſed, <hi>Ne nauceam ciem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is ſtrange I confeſſe for men to behold what Art dooth &amp; can doe with the meaneſt materialls that nature affords, when ſhe <hi>vndertakes</hi> to worke;<note place="margin">The Refiners of Gold and Siluer in London.</note> for I haue ſometimes ſeene good and pure <hi>Bullion</hi> both drawne and refined from the durt and duſt whereon the workemen ſtood: but theſe clenſe by water, and then purge by fire, and their working may be ſeene.</p>
               <p>Nay, I haue often admired, and with ioy beheld the ſtore of currant coyne in fine ſiluer and pure gold, that ſometimes was drawne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the ſhorlings of our Fells,<note place="margin">The Duch new Drapery of Bayes, Sayes, &amp;c, firſt deuiſed in <hi>Sand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich,</hi> and from thence learned and ſet vp elſwhere within the Realme. <hi>no we.</hi>
                  </note> the refuſe of our woolles, and ſweepings of our <hi>Staples,</hi> by the induſtry of <hi>Art,</hi> and helpe of fire and water. But theſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers</hi> are <hi>Artiſts</hi> indeed, that attend vpon theyr <hi>Trades,</hi> and concurre in their labour; theyr dooings are ſeene,<note place="margin">The only Patterne of a free Staple.</note> their Perſons knowne, their worke ſquard out by the Standard of Truth, and their Wares made vendible, onely by degrees of Goodnes.<note place="margin">Lex <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eritatis.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe <hi>Artiſts</hi> worke in Gods Name, whoſe <hi>Elixar Goodnes,</hi> by the miſterie of their Trades, turnes their worke unto Mettalls, and their Mettalls into <hi>Bullion,</hi> to ſerue our publique Myntes, that Marchants at their <hi>Ports</hi> may haue to pay their <hi>Tributes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they paſſe the Seas in ready currant Coyne,<note place="margin">Lex Iusticiae.</note> by the rules of <hi>Iuſtice.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe are our skilfull Workmen,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Lex Sapientie et ordinis.</hi> Beſides the Kings &amp; townes Seales, they haue 3. Seales to diſtinguiſh the worth of euery mans wates and worke, and that which deſerues not the worſt Seale, is cut into peeces, or put by to be amended, as being no wayes vendible at home nor a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broade.</note> whoſe orderly proceedings for the vſe of Goodnes, by the waights of Iuſtice, and skales of Truth, giuing euery man his Right, to <hi>Good, Better</hi> and <hi>Beſt,</hi> in the value of his worke, by the warrant of their SEALES, makes <hi>Deity</hi> in nature to be generally adored, and <hi>Induſtry</hi> in Art to be more or leſſe admired, to the ſpeciall praiſe and profit of thoſe <hi>Perſons</hi> and <hi>Places</hi> that firſt or laſt affoord them.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>Theſe are our <hi>honeſt Sacriſtaines,</hi> and ſure friendes to <hi>Trafficke,</hi> fit for our Altars of <hi>Vnity</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">They haue 12 ſworne men (beſides vnder officers,) that as Iudges exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine each mans worke before it paſſe the Seales: who being skilfull in all the Trades that belong to theyr Drapery, are impartriall Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurets of all Defaults, aſwell in ſpin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, weauing, fulling, and dying, as working, for the Buyers behooſe, euen to the mulct, and recompence of a thred and a farthing.</note> whoſe religious affections to the practiſe of Iuſtice, ſo bleſſe their Endeuours, that all men admiring the <hi>Beautie</hi> and <hi>Bounty</hi> of their Induſtries and worke, deſire to poſſeſſe them before Gold &amp; Siluer, to our <hi>Soueraignes</hi> great <hi>Honour,</hi> and his <hi>Peoples</hi> ſpeciall <hi>wealth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe deale not with our Cuſtomes, nor obtrude vppon our Subſidies, but teaching the way how to find out the one, and with allacritie how to pay the other, attend on <hi>Honeſtum</hi> &amp; <hi>Vtile</hi> ſtill together: O that our <hi>Fleeſe-wooll</hi> were thus vndertaken, &amp; our <hi>Broad-clothes</hi> but made and dreſt in this manner!</p>
               <p>Laſtly:<note place="margin">The <hi>Staples</hi> of <hi>Kent</hi> in <hi>E:</hi> 1. <hi>E:</hi> 2. &amp; <hi>Edward</hi> 3. time, kept at <hi>Sandwich</hi> and <hi>Canterb:</hi> (where nowe they of the Duch Church dwell,) was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued firſt for 15. yeres to <hi>Brid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges,</hi> &amp; after placed at <hi>Calice,</hi> the loſſe wherof, being now 50. yeeres ſince, would draw on a ſpeciall Diſcourſe beſides this PRIMER.</note> Theſe I ſay, and none but theſe, (for all theyr follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers elſwhere, haue fayld in their Rules, and crazd their credit,) are the childrens children of our former holy Prieſtes, that firſt found out the <hi>Pit</hi> in this <hi>Deſert</hi> of our Land, wherein ſo long a goe the<note n="*" place="margin">Read the ſecond of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chab: chap: <hi>1.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Fire</hi> was hid that ſanctified all our Tributes, and with the muddy moyſture onely that therein they found, (as our Sun did lately ſhine,) drew downe that heauenly heat which warmd our frozen <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and would reuiue our <hi>Staples,</hi> if WISDOME ſaw it good,) euen when the <hi>Pit</hi> was dry, and to all mens know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge the <hi>Fire</hi> was ſpent and gone.</p>
               <p>But theſe <hi>Farming Vndertakers,</hi> or <hi>vndertaking Farmers,</hi> ſeeme men of other skill, &amp; different profeſſions:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>An</hi> Antitheſis <hi>between the former</hi> Vndertakers <hi>of</hi> Sandwich, <hi>and thoſe now of</hi> London. Tritemiae Abbas de occulta philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phia: Ioannes Baptiſta de Porta: De fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiuis literarum Notis,</note> who drawing their Doctrine fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Tritemius Abbas Steganographia,</hi> and <hi>de Portas</hi> lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned workes, of their priuate Experience, haue altered all our Rules of <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile,</hi> to <hi>Lucri bonus odor ex re qualibet,</hi> and made an Art of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> to purge her ſpirits by, and refine her Tributes, from all the vertuous vices &amp; vicious vertues of <hi>Leekes, Onyons,</hi> and <hi>Garlicke:</hi> by a kind of diſtillation &amp; ſtrange<note n="*" place="margin">Theyr new Booke of Rates.</note> 
                  <hi>Limbecke</hi> of their owne.</p>
               <p>Now 1.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> how theſe men worke. 2.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> What men they are. 3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whence their doctrine comes. And 4.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> whereto it tendes, are curious Queſtions, and may be worth the ſpelling.</p>
               <p>For if heauenly <hi>Goodnes</hi> be the life of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> from whence as <hi>Trades</hi> doe ſwarue they turne againe to Nothing. And <hi>Golde</hi> and <hi>Siluer</hi> our choſen Materialls, by true proportions to fix this <hi>Goodnes</hi> in, as we haue learnd to ſpell: Then worke not theſe in <hi>Gods Name,</hi> like plaine-meaning Men, but as confident,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">How they worke.</note> care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and therefore dangerous <hi>Empericks,</hi> that ſhunne the Rules of <hi>Truth,</hi> who finding our <hi>Trades</hi> all ſubiect to <hi>Monopolies,</hi> and apt to be contracted, bring all our <hi>Miſteries</hi> to be pounded in one <hi>Morter,</hi> and there ſo ſqueiſe the Braines of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and refine her <hi>Tributes:</hi> that our <hi>Ports</hi> beeing once confounded as well as our <hi>Staples, Honour</hi> might doe them Homage, and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique <hi>Vtilitie</hi> become their priuate gaine.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Currant Coyne</hi> the Soule of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and our Soueraignes
<pb facs="tcp:15002:21"/>onely <hi>Trade,</hi> be thoſe proportions of Number and Weight to buy &amp; ſell by that makes <hi>Goodnes</hi> vendible for all our behoofes. Then are theſe Vndertaking-Farmers, <hi>Marchants,</hi> that (Trade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe themſelues) liue by buying and ſelling, and ſo by buying to ſell againe: that rayſing all their profits from others Trades and paynes,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/>
                  <note place="margin">What men they are:</note> are bound to pay their homage before they paſſe our <hi>Ports,</hi> with purpoſe to tranſport our <hi>Goodnes</hi> croſſe the Seas. And therefore made by Name incapable and incompatible to vndertake our Functions, or deale with our Tributes. As men ſpecially forbidden by the Statute-lawes and wiſdome of our Land,<note place="margin">14 <hi>R:</hi> 2. No Marchants that deale with ſtraights of Shyppes, or haue Shyps of theyr owne, or keepe any Whatſes, &amp;c. ſhall haue to do with the receipt of Cuſtomes, &amp;c. <hi>Item</hi> 20 <hi>H:</hi> 6. Cap: 5.</note> to obtrude vpon our <hi>Cuſtomes:</hi> much leſſe our Subſidies of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage,</hi> leaſt Marchants farming Marchants, &amp; ſo goe free themſelues, preſume to be like Kings or Princes fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes; to whom alone ſuch Rights are due, and therefore to none other, as beeing the onely knots to tye <hi>Maieſtie</hi> and <hi>Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altie</hi> ſo faſt and ſure together. Now, who ſtriues to out-runne the Lawes, makes haſt but to confuſion. But ſuch it ſeemes are theſe, by the courſe of their proceedings. And therfore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell, if turning all our freedoms into their bondage, and all our birth-rights into their Farme or purchaſe: from all the <hi>Goodnes Trafficke</hi> hath, and all the <hi>Loue</hi> our Marchants beare to our <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trons</hi> happie being; they gaine a maſſe of priuate wealth, by do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a world of harme.</p>
               <p>If <hi>Exchange</hi> of <hi>Goodnes</hi> by Gold &amp; Siluer, the <hi>Body</hi> &amp; <hi>Blood</hi> of <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> (repreſented to vs in <hi>currant Coyne,</hi>) be the Spirit of <hi>Trafficke,</hi> and myſticall Cyment that glewes ſo faſt together the mutuall coniunction betweene <hi>Soueraignes</hi> &amp; <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects,</hi>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/>
                  <note place="margin">Whence theyr Doctrine comes.</note> by <hi>Loue</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> as religious Iuſtice hath taught vs to beleeue.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vſury</hi> firſt practiſed in <hi>Rome,</hi> by the Bancks of <hi>Iewes</hi> there, and in other Chriſtian Countries, to draw home the Popes <hi>Peter-pens,</hi> and other ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions vpon the Nations &amp; king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms that obeyd their Religion.</note> Then drawe theſe <hi>Vndertakers</hi> their Methods all from ROME, where firſt was taught the doctrine that enchaunts and tranſubſtantiates our <hi>Euchariſticke Sacraments,</hi> (repreſenting to vs the <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Blood</hi> of CHRIST, by <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine,</hi>) to <hi>Idolatrous Maſſes,</hi> and our Chriſtian <hi>Exchange</hi> into Iewiſh <hi>V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Laſtly, if the KING be our Honour, the PRINCE our Sun, <hi>Trafficke</hi> the Chariot, and <hi>Shypping</hi> the wheeles that beare our <hi>glorious Lights:</hi> Theſe beeing but the Horſes, that ſo proudly ſet forward to vndertake our <hi>Goodnes,</hi> and drawe vs all in try<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph: Foreſeeing as I did, (my ſtanding made mee ſee, &amp; my ſeeing mooud my Conſcience not to hold my peace,) both the looſenes of their raynes; their byt within theyr teeth, and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of their courſe ouer Hills and Dales, bawkes and many by<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes, and all without a <hi>Coach-man</hi> or <hi>Guyde</hi> that I would ſpy. (They commaunding all,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/>
                  <note place="margin">Whereto their Doctrine tendes.</note> and controleable by none for hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of their Farme) I could not (my good Lords) out of Dutie and zeale to our <hi>Patrons</hi> ſafety, and all your happy beeings, but
<pb facs="tcp:15002:21"/>giue Caution heere-to-fore of the fiercenes of their Courage, and deſperate Carreere; that ſuch as ſtood ſo nigh them, might be warnd at leaſt to looke but to their heeles. But ſith like ſleeping <hi>Minotaures</hi> they nowe poſſeſſe the<note n="*" place="margin">LONDON.</note> 
                  <hi>Center</hi> of all our great Abuſes, and inextricable <hi>Errors,</hi> and threatning all our Trades with daily, monthly, and yeerely Tributes, make <hi>Traf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficke</hi> offer ſacrifice to<note n="1" place="margin">Extortion.</note> 
                  <hi>Remphan,</hi> &amp; to<note n="2" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury.</note> 
                  <hi>Rymmon:</hi> Let THE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SEVS now take heede, and ARIADNE looke about her; and with a ſmyle at leaſt, at laſt reuiue the Spirits of their deſpiſed <hi>Schollers,</hi> whoſe wits haue no wills, and Endeuours no Ends, but how to ſpell, and learne to read theyr Countries <hi>weale,</hi> the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique <hi>Good,</hi> and Soueraignes ſpeciall <hi>Honour,</hi> that <hi>Honeſtum</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tile</hi> might ſtill hold hands together. A ſmyle (I meane) of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to th' <hi>Out-Ports</hi> of this Land, aſwell as that of <hi>London:</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe, though <hi>Iuſtice</hi> haue a quickning power,<note place="margin">PREHEMINENCE. PREROGATIVE.</note> and may protect our beeings; yet <hi>Grace</hi> it is relieues vs all, and <hi>Mercy</hi> makes vs liue.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>By this which hath been ſpeld, your <hi>Wiſdoms</hi> now may read, to what diſtreſſe and miſery your <hi>Publicans</hi> are brought. That beeing Men as docible in Religion, as capable of Reaſon; Free men by their birthes, and of beſt education, Men euerie vvay made happy, ſaue in their names and callings: and in nothing yet more wretched then the Places of their Functions, (for I meane the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> onely, let <hi>London</hi> cleere it ſelfe,) are not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding in worſe caſe, (if worſe may be) then were thoſe <hi>Brickmakers</hi> that ſometimes wrought in <hi>Egypt,</hi> who vvanting meanes to do their taske, had notwithſtanding their idle Task-Maiſters, whoſe credits had no beeing but in their diſgrace, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded euen by thoſe that ſhould attend vppon vs, yea <hi>Sear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers</hi> and <hi>Sinners.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But as the caſe now ſtands, ſith all make loue to Tributes, &amp; catch our Functions from vs, High and low, Rich and poore, both Noble and ignoble,<note place="margin">All catch &amp; hunt for Cuſtomes, but ſhun the Name of Cuſtomers.</note> becauſe our Leſſons ſpell pure Siluer and fine Gold: and yet our Names they ſcorne. Let <hi>Iealouſie</hi> be called for, and let <hi>Impudency</hi> ſmell, what <hi>Ignorance</hi> hath added, and <hi>Extremity</hi> reformed in the abuſes of our <hi>Schooles,</hi> by ſpelling well the Letters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> The: Moores <hi>Epigram,</hi> De fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus abolendis.</note> but miſtaking the purpoſe of a graue and wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie Counſellor, that ſometimes gaue aduiſe in this very caſe of ours.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Sectile ne tetros porrum tibi ſpiret odores</l>
                  <l>Protinus á porro fac mihi cepevores. &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <q>Leaſt eating<note n="1" place="margin">Cuſtomer.</note> 
                  <hi>leekes</hi> (ſaith he) ſhould cauſe thy breth to ſmell Take<note n="2" place="margin">Controller.</note> 
                  <hi>Onyons</hi> ſtrong, that ſent will ſoone allay; And if thereby the ſauour ſeeme t'excell,
<pb facs="tcp:15002:22"/>
                  <note n="3" place="margin">Superviſors.</note> 
                  <hi>Garlicke</hi> be ſure will driue them both away: But if the ſtincking breath of <hi>Garlicke</hi> ſtay, What helpes vs then?<note n="4" place="margin">Farmors.</note> 
                  <hi>Tabacco?</hi> no, but at a word I thinke, There is a thing can<note n="5" place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndertakers.</note> 
                  <hi>Vndertake</hi> to make a viler ſtinke.</q>
               <p>And let Experience now ſhow, and Truth be bold to ſpeak, and tell them to their faces,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nota.</hi> This is meant by the myld diſcre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Cuſtomers</hi> in collecting the <hi>Subſidies</hi> of <hi>Tonnage</hi> and <hi>Pondage</hi> onely. For as for Cuſtomes which are ſo ſought for, and ſaid to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed, how generally ſoeuer theyr Name and Title runne: they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuppoſe alwaies our <hi>Staples.</hi> But our <hi>Staples</hi> beeing tranſplanted; as the Societies that haue engroſt them, muſt giue the K: and State account how they haue beſtowed them, and whether they be gone: So by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence, our Coſtomes.</note> that ſtriue to raiſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king our diſgrace: That God did put and place as much Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and Pleaſure, (I ſay Profit as Pleaſure,) harts-eaſe, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, in the quiet endeuours of <hi>Customers</hi> (ſo long as they were truſted,) through <hi>Mercy, Loyaltie</hi> and <hi>Loue;</hi> as the deuill is able apt and wont, to mingle care and comber, loſſe and ſhame in the turbulent vndertakings of Extremitie, by Extortion and Shyfts.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>And thus at laſt, the world may ſee and all men vnderſtand, in our Diſgrace, the KINGS great loſſe, and <hi>Kingdoms</hi> greater wrong. For beſides that both our <hi>Cuſtomes</hi> with our <hi>Staples,</hi> are gone or conuaid out of ſight, (the ground of all our woes, that wee can no wayes mend,) our <hi>Coyne</hi> and our <hi>Exchange,</hi> beeing turnd into <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſury,</hi> by Subiects like to Kings, or like to Princes fellowes: our <hi>Marchants</hi> by <hi>Societies</hi> call all men <hi>Enterlopers</hi> that are not of their Sects, or linckt with them together. Our <hi>Arts</hi> engroſt by men of diuers <hi>Trades.</hi> Our <hi>Trades</hi> doe meete in <hi>Companies,</hi> our <hi>Companies</hi> at <hi>Halls,</hi> and our <hi>Halls</hi> become <hi>Mono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polies</hi> of Freedome, tyde to <hi>London:</hi> where all our <hi>Crafts</hi> &amp; <hi>My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steries</hi> are ſo layd vp together, that outrunning all the prudence &amp; wiſedom of the Land,<note place="margin">Brewers made free of Bakers, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers free of Grocers, Grocers free of Fiſhmongers, Fiſhmongers free of Goldſmithes, and all men free of <hi>Coynage,</hi> that only ſerues for Kings.</note> men liue by Trades they neuer learnd, nor ſeeke to vnderſtand. By meanes whereof, all our Creekes ſeeke to one Riuer, all our Riuers run to one Port, all our Ports ioyne to one Towne, all our Townes make but one Citty, and all our Citties but Suburbes to one vaſt, vnweldy, and diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derlie <hi>Babell</hi> of buildings, which the worlde calls <hi>London:</hi> and <hi>London</hi> likewiſe co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tracted in it ſelfe, is made a Forreſt of ſhyfts, and Wildernes of ſinne. Where <hi>Trafficke</hi> liues confind, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſt by Rats and Mice,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trafficke</hi> poſſeſt with Spirits.</note> and ſpirits of the Ayre, of whom as of Harpies may truly now be ſaid:</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Triſtius haud istis Monſtrum, nec ſaeuior vlla</l>
                  <l>Peſtis et ira Deûm ſtygijs ſeſe extulit vndis.</l>
               </q>
               <q>No monſters like to theſe may hap, nor curſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God befall, Nor from the pit of hell ariſe,<note place="margin">Searching wayters, &amp; wayting Searchers.</note> to plague the Realme withall:</q>
               <q>
                  <l>Is ſo by fits tormented, both by water and by Land,</l>
                  <l>That how to helpe her now, we doe not vnderſtand.</l>
               </q>
               <p>But though fayth be frayle, and all our credit gone, yet dooth our vowes, compell vs ſtill by faſting and by prayer to doe our beſt Endeuours.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:15002:22"/>For, faultes there are no doubt, euer were, and euer will be many; PERFECTION knowes no reſidence but <hi>Heauen.</hi> And if we ſay we haue no ſinne, there is no Truth within vs. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we wiſh, and pray all thoſe that reade this ALPHABET &amp; PRIMER, to ioyne with our Deuotions, and with pure harts and humble voyce, to the Throne of GOD and his heauenly Grace, to pray but in this manner, ſaying after mee.</p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <p>
                              <note place="margin">Cuſtomers generall Confesſion.</note>
                              <hi>ALmighty and moſt mercifull Father, wee haue erred and ſtrayed from thy wayes like loſt ſhéepe, we haue followed too much the deuices and deſires of our owne harts, wee haue offended againſt thy holy Lawes, wee haue left vndoone the things we ſhould do, and we haue done the things we ought not to doe, and there is no health in vs. But thou O Lord haue mercie vpon vs miſerable offenders, ſpare thou vs, O Lorde, which confeſſe our ſaultes, and reſtore them that are penitent, according to thy promiſes, declared vnto mankind in Chriſt Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu our Lord: and graunt O moſt mercifull Father for his ſake, that wee may héereafter liue a godly, a righteous, and a ſober life, to the glory of thy holy Name.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>¶ A Prayer for the Kings Maieſtie.</head>
                           <p>O Lord our heauenly Father, high and mightie, King of Kings, Lord of Lords, the onely Ruler of Princes,<note place="margin">Cuſtomers daily and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Prayers.</note> which dooſt from thy Throne behold all the dwellers vpon Earth, wée humbly beſéech thee with fauour to behold our moſt gracious and Soueraigne Lord King <hi>IAMES,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">&amp; per ſe.</note> and ſo repleniſh him with the grace of thy holy Spirit, that hee may alwaies encline to thy will, and walke in thy way. Endue him plentifully with heauenly gyfts, graunt him in health and wealth long to liue, that finally after this life, he may attaine to euerlaſting ioy and felicitie, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>¶ A Prayer for the Queene and Prince, and other the King and Queenes Children.</head>
                           <p>ALmighty God, which haſt promiſed to be a Father of thine Elect and of their ſéede, wee humbly beſeech thee to bleſſe and preſerue our gracious Queene <hi>ANNE,</hi> Prince <hi>HENRIE,</hi> and all the King and Queenes royall Progenie. Endue them with thy holy Spirit, enrich the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with thy heauenly Grace, proſper them with all happines, and bring them to thine euerlaſting kingdome, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Sauiour.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <pb facs="tcp:15002:23"/>
                           <head>A Prayer for the Clergie, Lords of the Counſaile, all Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, all Nations, and the Common-People.</head>
                           <p>ALmighty &amp; euerlaſting God, we moſt humbly beſéech thée to illuminat all <hi>Biſhops, Paſtors,</hi> &amp; <hi>Miniſters</hi> of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Church, with the true knowledge and vnderſtanding of thy Word, and that both by their preaching and liuing, they may ſet it foorth, and ſhew it accordingly. To endue the Lords of his Maieſties moſt honorable <hi>PREVY-COVNSELL,</hi> &amp; all the <hi>Nobility,</hi> with grace,<note place="margin">Con, per ſe.</note> wiſedome, and vnderſtanding. To bleſſe and keepe our <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> giuing them grace to execute Iuſtice, and maine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Truth. To giue all Nations <hi>Vnitie, Peace</hi> and <hi>Concord,</hi> And finally, to giue vs an hart to loue and dread thée, and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently to liue after thy Commandements. Grant this, O Lord, for the honour of our Aduocate, &amp; onely Mediator Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
               <p>
                  <hi>THe</hi> Customers <hi>of the <hi>Out-Ports</hi> proſtrate Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the KING our <hi>Soueraigne,</hi> for his Sonne the PRINCES ſake, to be made but as able as they are euery way willing to do their Duties; that eating the Bread of good Conſcience daily, and freed from temptations of Obloquy and ſhyfts, his Kingdome beeing come, may ſtill continue; and his Will perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in all Places alike; Forgiuing all as they would be forgiuen: Conclude this their PRIMER with the ſanctified words; and enclude their Petition within the compaſſe of that effectuall Prayer which our Lord &amp; Sauiour (the Sonne of GOD) hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded, and taught, ſaying;</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <p>OUr Father which art in heauen, hallowed be thy Name, thy Kingdome come, thy will be done in Earth, as it is in Heauen: Giue vs this day our daily Bread: and forgiue vs our Treſpaſſes, as we forgiue them that treſpaſſe againſt vs: Let vs not be led into temptation, but deliuer vs from euill: For thine is the <hi>KINGDOME,</hi>
                              <note place="margin">Tittle, tittle, tittle, Eſt Amen.</note> the <hi>POVVER,</hi> and the <hi>GLORIE:</hi> for euer and euer. <hi>SO BE IT.</hi> Amen.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="prayer">
                           <head>¶ The Publicans humble Confeſſion and priuate Prayer.</head>
                           <l>Nil ſum, nulla miſer novi ſolatia, Maſſam</l>
                           <l>Humanam niſi quod tu quo<expan>
                                 <am>
                                    <g ref="char:abque"/>
                                 </am>
                                 <ex>que</ex>
                              </expan> 
                              <hi>CHRISTE</hi> geris.</l>
                           <l>Tume ſustenta, fragilem tu <hi>CHRISTE</hi> guberna,</l>
                           <l>Fac vt ſim Maſſae ſurculus <hi>Ipſe</hi> tuae.</l>
                           <p>
                              <hi>Magna, Magnus perficit DEVS.</hi>
                           </p>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </q>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:15002:23"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
